this is a follow-up
discussion I I don't remember the exact
date you can find out from the video on
YouTube probably but a few years ago at
this point um I had a conversation with
Casey and it was just sort of
um you know it was this topic that had
been bubbling around in the background
for a while like parsing programming
languages had bothered you like the way
it's discussed or whatever we go into
much more detail the talk um and I had
done it a bunch and then especially for
this programming language I'm working on
now I had to do a much more thorough and
serious job than ever because there's
just way more features in the language
and there's more weird cases that come
up and so you know the main gist of that
talk back then was like look this thing
that they call recursive descent parsing
which is a very technical term that what
it actually means is just write code the
way you normally would for any other
program
right um and don't do any of the crazy
[ __ ] that they teach you in college um
is the right way to write a parser like
unambiguously and it's much simpler and
you get better error messages and all
that anyone who's interested in that can
go watch that video now one of the
topics that came up you know toward the
middle or toward the end was the
operator precedence topic right and you
were like what do you do for operator
precedence and what I said at the time
was uh well you know I do what I think
is probably the second best thing thing
um which is I do this tree
rewriting which is just you know to
summarize it very briefly we'll go into
what this precedence problem is in a
second too if you don't understand it
um it was just like look anytime you
make a
node uh if there's a precedence problem
you can detect it by only looking at one
layer of the thing because by induction
everything else is correct so if you
just rewrite your tree with some random
function um then you're fine
and and you don't have to think about
any computer sciencey thing right and
that was a totally reasonable way to do
it um it certainly worked for nine or
something like that years depending on
how you count I mean the compiler was a
side project at first but you know a
long
time um you know beta shipped to
hundreds of happy beta users using it
but then you know Christmas time and New
Year's is often a
very productive programming time for me
because or game design time honestly but
programming is easier when you're
overworked um
so uh you know I did a bunch of stuff
but then sort of at the end of my New
Year's time I was like
hey let me you know I think something
initiated this like I wanted to change
some feature in the thing and I was like
oh I have to go deal with this parser
thing and it felt a little bit annoying
so I said hey let me just go back and
see what I can do about the precedent
situation can I do it what I said was
the first best way and can I do it as
cleanly as possible and can I really
understand it clearly because part of
the problem is part of the reason I
didn't do it that way in the first place
way back when I started the compiler was
I would go read some of these references
and they're like really hard to
understand and you know I don't exactly
see how this relates to what I'm really
trying to do and all this and we'll
we'll go through some of those
references but the point being um last
week I think it was Saturday one week
ago today
uh I just rewrote the way precedence
works in the parser um and got rid of
all the tree rewriting and it uh it
works great and I did that for you know
the programming language is not a toy
language it's a C++ competitor language
with a pretty complex grammar and so I
just want to not even talk through the
method so much cuz the method is I mean
it's so simple it's unbelievable that
it's even been a problem for decades
right that's really the point that I
want to get to is it's so simple it's
crazy and if anybody had ever just sat
down and said look here's the thing and
in fact there are a couple references
that kind of do that and I'll I'll go to
those
but the problem is they're hard to find
on the modern internet like yeah I would
say that like there's there's been a
couple things that people have pointed
me to I think actually after the
discussion that we had where like it's
actually really simple like here's
here's two examples that like I wrote up
for you it's like five lines of code or
whatever right and I'm like oh uh and
and you would never know that if like
primarily what someone handed you was
the Dragon book right you would you
would have no idea that anyone had ever
figured that out because you would have
assumed well surely they would rewrite
this part of the book if you could do it
but they don't and so it's very leading
to people who are getting into this
because the things that they will find
uh end up being like uh really
obfuscating for some reason yeah since
you're on this we'll go back in a second
and explain what this is for people who
are lost right but you know so the
Dragon book was 1986 I went back and
looked right and that's sort of based on
this green dragon book which was an
earlier thing from 1977 right um a green
dragon book Yeah we actually had a few
copies of it at Berkeley too it was what
you would buy at the used University
Bookstore okay if you couldn't get the
other
one um so this the the sort of the paper
that everyone cites that lays out how to
do this is this topown operator
precedence paper from
1973 which predates the Dragon book by
13 years okay that's that's amazing and
even the green dragon book by a few
years um but actually that's actually
the same thing as is something that dyra
did in a paper called an alol 60
translator for the X1 right which how
would you ever think about reading that
paper from the title right um but it's
also it's OB fiscated because it's this
thing called shunting yard algorithm
which is about stack manipulation to to
put things in this fourth like thing
right which doesn't really look like
very much like what you want to do if
you're parsing a programming language
however it's the same it's like
understanding what order the operations
need to occur in and then making the
correct output right and the making the
correct output step is different but the
understanding it is is the same um I
didn't really try to read that paper
though too because the more you go back
in time the harder computer science you
know Publications are to read um because
everything was different and you don't
have context and a lot of terms mean
different things now than they meant
then and stuff um but also honestly what
happened with this was um I also just
have very little patience now for trying
to read things so if I start trying to
read a few references and I just there's
this thing that happens on the internet
where there's a miasma of stuff and you
start to get lost and you're like okay
this person is saying it's easy but
maybe they're a bozo maybe they're not a
bozo right I don't I don't know and the
way that I the main way that I know how
to know if someone's a bozo is to just
go figure it out and then I have a basis
on which to judge right um yes yes I've
noticed that I tried to send send you
the lp fifo paper and you were like I
don't know they don't explain the
algorithm or something and you didn't
read it and I'm like no it's a good
paper I didn't like that paper okay it's
a good paper anyway so so to provide a
little context for people uh who aren't
into parsers about what exactly the
problem is again we we covered this also
I think in the previous video so I'm
going to go through it really fast
but one of the things about compilers
and and parsing the input text that I'm
never probably going to argue with is
this token abstraction and we're going
to assume it here so you get raw text in
a file coming in and you have some part
of your program that breaks that into
slightly higher level things that are
easier to think about and manipulate so
like is something the name of a variable
or is something a number or is it like a
string literal or whatever that happens
before what we're talking about so you
have something that reads characters one
at a time and breaks it into a stream of
those now that's not actually strictly
necessary to do um I've never done it
any other way but I'm just not not going
to argue with it here I have no
experience doing something else than
that probably people in the early days
of computers did do something else than
that um so then what a parser looks like
so here's just a simple function for
like P parsing a binary Operator by the
way there's a lot of little code
Snippets in here I just picked like this
is a pseudo code that is kind of like C
but with less pun punctuation that's all
I'm doing so um nothing special so
there's a function like if you want a
parse a binary operator without
recursion or anything just like a plus b
something simple like that you call like
parse Leaf which gives you this thing
that's like maybe it's a number maybe
it's an identifier and so you could get
anything you could get a plus b you
could get 3 plus b right you could get
seven uh
times hello which in a reasonable
programming language is going to be an
error but in some is not
right um you're right
so uh you
know so so there's this fundamental uh
layering of functions where you say I
want a leaf and then I'm going to look
at what the operator is so here for
parse Leaf I would parse this three and
then the input is like plus b and I say
what's the operator and it's like oh
it's plus so we eat the plus and then we
parse the next Leaf which is B and then
we make a binary actually so here my
binary is a plus b so you know then we
make a little binary tree and what this
is is a representation of it's like a
node with a left pointer and a right
pointer that could point at maybe other
binary operators even though this code
can't generate that here it's just
pointing at two leaves right A plus b
right um now of course if you want a
parse more than a plus b the typical
thing you do in a parser is you make
this effectively recursive whether the
code's actually recursive or not right
um it needs to be able to you need to be
able to refer to other binary nodes and
stuff right
um I'm not sure why I did this extra
step here um this is just a version of
parse expression that could return
either a leaf or a binary operator based
on what the next token is right this is
a very typical thing to do so again if
you say parse Leaf you get a maybe just
because you were trying to show like
okay so if we want to do more than one
expression this is how we do it like
more than one that's what I'm trying to
get to down here I wrote this like 5
days ago so whatever I don't totally
remember but so if you have a longer
thing like a plus b plus C plus d right
then this can be recursive and here it
it actually is recursive in fact like it
calls itself but if you don't like
recursion you can always convert a
recursive function to a loop um it just
might get really messy depending on
what's going on um anyway so if it's
recursive you could say let's parse a
leaf which here will be a right you can
get the next token that'll be plus and
then if that's a binary operator which
in this case it is we call parse
expression again which will take this as
input right and then that'll call parse
expression again take that as input uh
and that'll call parse expression again
which will take just d as input which
will return You A D um and then you make
binary operators going on the way up I
actually skipped that step here so the
the final tree you get out of this is
this thing right
um a a on the left a root node right a
on the left and then B on the left of
the child and then the CD binary tree
and so all the leaves are in there you
can use your favorite computer science
way of navigating this tree however you
want
now it's worth pointing
out why why is this a tree like what
what does the tree do well okay before
we say that let's just go uh you know
the point that I was making about
talking through the recursion here is
just that the first thing actually
constructed is sort of this D leaf and
then you come back up the recursion and
now that you know what was on the right
hand side now you have a CD right now
you have a BCD now you have an
ABCD
okay this is the tree structure that is
naturally created by doing this simple
dumb thing right it's this right Leaning
Tree
if you have a longer and longer
expression it'll just keep going you
like extend this ladder to the
right okay this may be out of scope for
this discussion but I might also ask the
question at this point for
clarity if one were naively to look at
that explanation and hasn't worked on
parsers before yeah one might have the
question why recurse down to D and then
work back up the program stack to
construct plus C plus b plus a why not
just put a in when you encounter it then
create the plus node and then create the
B and so on like like what is the value
of using recursion at all yes well um
the answer in this exact case for as far
as we've gone is that it's an arbitrary
choice you can do it the way that you
said and in fact we will do it that way
in a little bit okay never mind sorry
no no no it's totally it makes sense
because it's it's so you know basically
if you went to school at Berkeley like I
did they love recursion and they drill
it into you and so it's the it's the way
that you would do things right okay yep
um okay actually maybe that other
version is recursive too but you could
convert it to a loop it's again it's not
a big deal um okay now just to give some
context about what this tree is right uh
what it just represents is operations
that you do in what order right so the
plus you know represents I'm going to
add two things and what's on the left is
the left thing that I add and what's on
the right is the right thing that I add
right and if if what's on the right is
more complex than just a leaf then it
sort of means you don't know the answer
yet you have to go do that stuff and
then you can do the plus right so in
this case it's like a plus what I don't
know it's whatever this is okay okay
well that's B plus what I don't know
that's C plus d oh I know what c plus d
are so I can add this right and then I
can that gives me what to add to B and
that gives me what to add to a so what
the tree is effectively doing I probably
say this later too but what this tree is
effectively doing is it's parenthesizes
your expression like this okay right and
the way to remember that that's really
easy is if you see parentheses in the
equation it's the same as like circling
a sub tree like if you can Circle a sub
tree without cutting any uh cutting
sideways then that's the parentheses in
the equation yeah yeah it's the same
thing
okay now here's the whole point of what
we're talking about which is you want to
be able to not have to type this all the
time right and it's natural and
everybody's used to being able to say
something like a plus b * C plus d but B
* C is supposed to happen first that's
just something we decided as human
beings that we want to do um and of
course plus and times are not the only
example of this it comes up in a number
of cases but this is the simplest one
probably that people understand um that
said this one seems more
arbitrary because like it is a human
choice but there's other
ones I don't know I guess if you were
willing to put parenthesis around
literally everything this wouldn't be a
problem but it just comes up a lot right
so if we run the same code on a plus b *
C plus d right well this code didn't
care any about any detail of the
operator right so we're going to get the
same output which is this this same tree
except instead of this plus up here
we're going to get a
times and by this parenthesis making
that I just did that gives us this right
I left out sort of the outer parenthesis
but yeah which is not what we would
consider the right answer right um this
is what we would consider the right
answer is parentheses in the
middle okay and then here's where I was
going to rant about the Dragon book and
stuff but uh we already started that um
so I will
say I mean I went to I went to college
starting in like you know 1989 when like
all the web stuff hadn't happened yet
but a lot of this other stuff was
considered old and established and just
the more I look at
it the more I feel like a lot of
computer science was just corrupt lazy
people who didn't really solve problems
I mean I hate to say it I hate to say it
but and this is just one instance of it
and not so these people weren't corrupt
lazy people and even maybe the Dragon
book people are not corrupt lazy people
they wrote a big book full of a it's a
really complicated book full of stuff
right but there was this horrible
malfunction that Casey already referred
to where this book got used as the
standard for how to teach compilers in
basically every certain certainly good
school computer science class and
probably everything else because what
else would you use and the problem
is it makes out parsing like it's really
really really hard and like an entire
science of its own and doesn't say much
about the rest of compilation which is
actually the hard part oh it's it's it's
horrible for that like it's like if you
read that book you would assume that
most of writing a compiler is trying to
get a parser working yeah and then you
like generate some very simple code from
the pars Tre afterwards now just so
people don't know just so people don't
say you don't know what you're talking
about like oh you went to you went to
school in the Stone Age it's different
now so I have a current copy like this
is what you would buy off Amazon
now um oh wow can I see that can you
hold up that cover oh yeah it's awesome
it's it's got a computer generated cover
the old green dragon book has a horrible
you know hand Illustrated cover that's
just not involving computers in any way
and so they replaced it with like
whatever you could do in
1997 on a silicon Graphics wow no before
that 19 yeah I don't know anyway this it
has some additional chapters in the end
um where they talk a little bit about
data flow analysis and
like bite code and stuff but it's a
small part of the book
and the problem with all that stuff is
just they like touch on the topics and
each of these topics like really could
have a whole book and of course I don't
know but the point being like I think
the laziness is institutional it's not I
don't wish to pick on the Dragon book
too hard because the fact
is the institution of Computer Science
Education could have well they did
accept the Dragon book as the thing that
they're going to teach and that's that's
what it is they could have
not done that right and and gone out and
dug up like a reading list of these old
papers at least or somebody else could
have made like a a different book and
well or you could say this was the main
thing that I was going to add about the
Dragon book as well is the Dragon book
also when you are handed it at least I'm
thinking of more the I think it was a
red dragon book that was the the the one
that I saw second edition yeah this is
this is the more modern computer Dragon
book I haven't seen that one but when
someone hands you the Red Dragon book
they were like this is the book to read
about compilers at implying that somehow
it's a good book to read about compiling
that is my makeup if someone handed it
to me and went this book actually sucks
but I don't have anything else to hand
you that's fine I've had to do that to
people uh before where it's like I don't
know of a good reference you can try
this but it's lousy the the dragon books
problem was people claimed it was good
yes mainly yes and it's not yeah anyway
so
uh if you look on the internet today
there's as you know a lot of trash
information and that's the main problem
there are some references that are okay
um uh you know like like I said I think
a few minutes ago when I went back and
read this old paper which is sort of
what what we're going to talk about what
it's based on um I think although I
don't know because honestly my eyes
glazed over and I didn't finish the
paper right but this is sort it's it's
unreadable dude
um but so here's some Modern references
that are more readable uh so although
okay they do a couple different things
and we'll get into it so this one uh is
what I looked at last week I didn't even
really read this one all the way I just
sort of skimmed it uh it's called
parsing Expressions by precedence
climbing here's the URL um will you know
what I'll paste this into chat for
anyone who wants um let me if I paste
this whole thing into chat that will
that work people can pick you're asking
a lot of twitch there I am let's
see no it didn't uh it didn't paste the
whole thing so here's part
one and then because it's more than like
you know a Twitter number of characters
and that was their competition or
whatever while you're doing stream stuff
do you want to move your camera up a bit
you're you're off the bottom fairly
frequently I think when
typing well no you know I just don't
want to I don't care fair
enough um okay
so so this one is the one that I read in
order to to figure out but I sort of
skimmed it it's like here's some code in
Python and the python code instead of
like an enum and C to decide what you're
doing it like uses strings and like
switches off the string it's like okay
okay we're not really reading this right
um but it is the basic idea uh now a lot
of people like this book crafting
interpreters which is also on the
internet and and when I posted about
this talk people were like oh I know
it's easy because I just read crafting
interpreters and it does recursive
descent parsing right okay here's the
thing what they do in this book is
recursive descent that will handle
precedence
however it's pretty slow and really ugly
and I do not recommend doing it that way
we can talk at the end about what this
is cu it's kind of interesting in this
like in terms of like how possibly
stupid can you make it this is maybe
even one step more stupid than what I'm
going to do um I don't recommend doing
it this way but it is like the polar
opposite of the Dragon book but that's
not I'm not bagging on the author of
this book either because he wrote A Blog
posting like 10 years before this book
came out where he talks about the
Precedence thing that we're going to
do I don't know why why he didn't do
that in the book though like maybe he
thought it was not as simple I don't
know but the the thing he does in the
book is like it's a little bit
unconscionable I don't know maybe that's
too strong of a word um unconscionable
not not quite it's just you know in that
way when you write
software not you when people out there
in the world just write software and
it's doing a lot of work for something
that should be simple right yeah yeah
and we'll talk about what that problem
is yeah
um uh the most approachable explanation
of this is actually this paper called
writing an interpreter in
go which if you're writing a compiler
not an interpreter and you're don't
program and go you probably wouldn't
read that um I guess I forgot to paste
the link in here but you can find this
by
searching uh anyway this is the most
approachable explanation that I found um
okay actually and just to quantify what
I did Saturday right so it took about it
took probably about six or seven hours
to do this conversion I would pause you
for one second here in my role as inter
no please interrupt as much as you want
and just say I think it might help now
at this point to explain what you were
doing because I think most people don't
probably know exactly what you were
doing and they couldn't go watch maybe
the previous video but it wasn't all
about that it was about other stuff as
well so just like when you say tree
rewrite you want give a quick example
people know what did Quicky example so
what we were saying before is if you
put a + b * C plus d into this code that
we showed already you get this thing
which is the wrong answer right and like
we said it sort of gets built from the
bottom up because it's the result of a
recursive function right um so what what
the code would
do after you've built C plus d that
part's fine and and we'll actually we
actually call this checking function
that I'm going to mention in a minute
about should we change the tree and it
looks at plus CD and it's like no that's
fine there's nothing that's vanilla plus
right so then we get back and before let
me just copy pasta
this what just happened okay max power
yeah exactly um so then you fall back
one level in recursion and you had a
times B and you were just waiting for
this and now you got this right and
you're like okay B * C plus d uh let's
pass it to the tree rewrite code and the
tree rewrite code would
say hey wait I'm at a node that's a
times and the thing on the right is a
binary and there's no parenthesis
because when you parenthesize something
I would put a flag on the node right and
it would say there's no parenthesis um
so I'm G to do a rewrite operation where
I
grab I grab um you sort of like Swizzle
the tree around right like let me you
basically want to turn this into um we
can just again right the right answer is
so this is
uh uh I'm going to put the outer
parentheses this is B * C plus d right
and you want to turn that into uh B time
C plus d right and so this is a right
Leaning Tree but again what I said about
the parentheses is you have to be able
to Circle it right so this is like a
left Leaning Tree actually um and
actually that fact will come up later so
what it does is it rewrites into um the
following
thing sorry I should have deleted that
first it probably looked confusing for a
minute right and how do you do this um
you can do this just by you keep the
binary node with the left here I mean
because it was the right that we
detected you know um you keep the node
with the left here and then you steal
the thing on the left of here and then
you move this one up and you child it
and it's a very you know y i i don't
want to try to draw those intermediate
operations in right but you just
basically you are you don't have to make
anything new because you have all the
right pointers in the right places you
just have to change who's pointing to
what right yep and that's what I did and
so to quantify this um the parser
without ignoring the tree change
operation for a minute the parser was
around 6,000 lines last week um 6300 or
something which some people would say oh
my God that's really big but like it's a
C++ competitor programming language with
like a lot of nodes there's like a lot
of syntax and so that's just what that
means um the lexical analyzer was around
2,000 lines um the tree rewriting code
was 350 lines so it's like not even
really that much code um but the the
thing that there's two things about
doing things this way right I'm going to
interrupt you one more time I apologize
yes uh just to finish up that part you
said you put a flag on things when
there's parentheses so I assume that
means something like well when you parse
a parent a open pen yeah you then call
like parse expression recursively or
something and when it finds the closed
pen then you take whatever you got back
from that and set the parenthetical fra
flag which then prevents any of these
things from yeah yeah it's actually a
little simpler than that um it's
basically what you said with one small
change that might be important for
people to understand um yeah when you
see an open pen you call parse
expression right um but parse expression
doesn't do the closed pen you do because
it'll stop whenever it sees something
that doesn't start an expression anymore
right which a Clos PR does so parse
expression doesn't know what the Clos PR
means but you know that you expect that
after parsing a full expression and if
you don't you can say a syntax error and
it's actually so one of the things about
these so-called recursive descent
parsers that's a really strong suit is
there much much better for error
reporting than uh you know all these
other systems of generating parsers and
here's the thing is error reporting is
the user interface of your programming
language like it's critically important
right
um yeah so so you don't you don't want
to phone it in you want to be good error
messages anyway so that's what I was
doing is I was rewriting this to this
now of course because this is the right
answer the goal is like how do you
create this as opposed to having to
rewrite it as a way to to say what we're
gonna do no you said you wanted to say
two things uh when I interrupted you and
I apologize uh oh uh well so there were
like I said I I just like excuse me for
some
reason the uh the Dragon book Illuminati
are trying to prevent me from speaking
oh yes with the voodoo doll
um
so the reason I did this was I just like
the idea of cleaning up the parser right
and finally understanding this thing
that I had kind of swept under the rug
and ignoring and ignored
um there's something good about this
tree rewriting aspect which is it often
makes code easier to right
because you can just write code that
parses some complicated construct and
you know if it I want to call that from
here oh but in some case when there's an
operator to the left maybe that operator
has to know about this thing and
whatever and it's like n just we'll fix
it in post right it's like fine yeah
yeah yeah and so an example of I mean
this is a very simple example but
there's in in programming languages
there are a lot of like you know binary
operators are very simple there are a
lot of more complex concept construct so
like you see if you see the keyword for
which comes in in one token right it's
very unambiguous what has to happen
after that um in C++ it's a little more
ambiguous because they have ways of
overloading it but in C it's like
actually I don't even know later latest
C probably has some weird stuff but in
classic C you see the word for and it's
like okay there's going to be an open
parentheses there's going to be three
statements with semicolons in between
and there's going to be a closed
parentheses as then a block which might
be a statement or it might you know you
just call your parse block function
which knows to look for either a
statement or some braces and stuff right
and that's you can write that in one
function and it's very clear like this
and then this and then this and that and
that and that and
um you
know sometimes when grammars get
complicated it's like oh well I want to
parse this thing in the middle of my
complicated construct but maybe it needs
to associate differently or whatever
yeah I don't want to go too much into
that because if you ever if you ever
decide to do a parser that way you will
discover this so there's a convenient
thing about it is it lets you paste over
things another way to say that is like
when you decide to parse things in the
middle of like just a hard-coded
function like
that like the the way the specific sub
functions that you call determine
precedence in a way right and if you
don't want to have some system for
negotiating precedence you could just
fix it later and it just it makes it
easy but it's one of those things where
it makes it easy in the beginning but
then like later after you've done it a
bunch there's like a lot of code and
it's not it's not a ton of code like I
said it was 350 lines but it's like oh
man I really have to
like if I have a bug I'm like not sure
if it's over here over there and
like it was more complex than I would
like right especially you can't you
can't step through the recursive descent
parser anymore and know if it's
operating correctly because it could be
be that it's operating incorrectly or it
could be that it's operating correctly
and the tree rewriter is operating
incorrectly so now you have to debug
both at the same time effectively which
just makes your job a little bit harder
not fantastic a little bit harder little
it's actually not that bad because they
are interleaved like the tree rewriting
doesn't operate at the root of the tree
it's like every time we're going to pass
you something back we call the thing
right but right if it was fully deferred
then it would be a real nightmare I I
would more classify it as just like it's
harder to think about and that's one of
the reasons why I want to talk about
this today again the goal of this is
expressing how absolutely simple this
solution is and we're in this world
where we're like complexity bound right
like we're just software is limited by
how hard things are to understand and
that's why I think this is such a
critical issue like anytime you can
identify something like this like we
need to Nuke all the over complicated
stuff from orbit it is the only way to
be sure that like software will be good
in the
future um so yeah anyway
um okay here's where we bust out the
spicy meme right oh so I made a spicy
meme just for this talk what what so
what I said was this thing that we made
is wrong okay because oh not in this
case not in the plus case actually
here's a another thing we'll say for
later is like if you're just plus a
bunch of integers you actually kind of
don't care about precedence here right
right if you're doing pedantic floating
point maybe you
I don't know but you know so there's
some things where you don't totally care
and we'll come up to that later again
um anyway the point was if you do a plus
b time C plus d you get this structure
and it's wrong okay but here's here's
the spicy
meme um I'm so ready for this yes uh the
spicy meme is that it's actually right
sometimes right um there are some cases
for which okay is that I mean
is that's going to Twitter I hope uh
sure yeah nobody will know what it's
about but
um uh I mean that has to go up right
now um so so it's actually right
sometimes and this is the key insight to
these papers and stuff which is here
let's say you have an expression such as
a is greater than like there's an if
statement around this right you're going
to
say just to if if this do something
right that's a real thing that happens
MH if it happens to be arranged in this
way the Precedence of greater than now
if you're just thinking about math
operators it might be weird to think
about greater than is like the same
thing as plus but in terms of a
programming language it basically is
it's an operator that takes two sides it
returns a value that's a Boolean right
and so um but the Precedence in C like
languages for example of greater than is
very low it's lowerer than plus and plus
is lower than times okay and if you
parenthesize this you get this right and
the tree version of this of course is
this which is exactly what that code
outputed right right so
like this is this is right sometimes and
so maybe you can use that right that's
well the the dumb guy on the bell curve
is like well I guess that's what we can
do right and then the smart guy is like
no like this means something it's like
the the mashed potatoes right the mashed
pot this means something yes okay well
okay if if this is the right thing for
this what if the Precedence goes the
opposite way obviously you could write
this thing right and it's parenthesize
that way and that's a left Leaning Tree
um you know we we just spoke a little
bit ago that you could turn the right
Leaning Tree into a left Leaning Tree by
rewrites but if you wanted to just
generate it how would you do that and
the answer is basically what Casey was
asking asking about before
um uh I'm trying to remember what I did
here um okay so here we have a version
of parsing a binary tree where you pass
in the left side as a parameter and then
you just keep calling this to get the
times B plus C less than D whatever
right so you pass in the left you say
get the next token if it's a binary
operator make a binary node otherwise
just return the left side and this
doesn't have to be a function this could
be inside a loop but for clarity I just
broke it into a piece right and just to
be clear I I I can just restate that
again make sure everyone gets it so
basically what John is saying here is
when we write the recursive descent
parser the first time it was an
arbitrary choice for us to decide to
build a right Leaning Tree meaning we
always were putting the next token
underneath our own binary operator but
we are not forced to do that we could
have just done it the other way where we
always put the thing on the left uh side
of the tree and by to do that we have to
pass down uh that to the to the
recursive call yeah and so I think you
know it it's sort
of which way you find easier to think
about um depends on just how you tend to
think about and solve problems you know
if you went to recursive school like I
did you probably build the right Leaning
Tree by default but iterative algorithms
tend to be more efficient than recursive
algorithms right I don't care what all
the tail recursion stands say um
yes so you know if you're trying to
build performance software you want to
think about loops and that kind of thing
right um because you know Loops can be
expanded into like Loops operating on a
wide number of things and whatever um
okay
so so if you have this thing that takes
a left hand side then you can just every
time you make a new sub tree you just
can just pass that in as the left hand
side and build more tree right which is
what this thing is doing this thing
another way instead of par single binary
you could call this like add the right
hand side onto a tree or whatever right
right and so this part this version of
parse expression starts by parsing a
leaf and this is the thing that's weird
for me to think about because in the
recursive
version the recursive function itself is
like I'm going to
parse um a left and then plus and then
the Right comes later and in this
version you give the left and the left
comes already and that was weird for me
to think about but the recursive version
is hard to think about too because you
have to be like oh this comes way later
after things happen so I don't know
right but anyway so here's here's how
this works is you you get the first Leaf
which in this case is a then you do this
Loop where you parse binary that'll eat
a plus b right and
then if it Returns the same thing we
gave it this might be a stupid way to do
the stopping condition but it's just the
way I did it right if because if this
doesn't see an operator it just returns
back the parameter right so like if we
just got that then just return that's
the answer we ran out of input or
whatever right otherwise just say the
left is the new binary node and then
just keep looping right and I believe
that's what you were suggesting before
yes I was I was kind of asking like yeah
or or I wasn't even suggesting you would
even necessarily use
uh recursion I was just saying like I
just grab a token I put it down I grab
another one I go okay it's a plus I link
it to left side I grab the next one it's
you know yeah that's exactly what this
is like if you don't make this a
separate function right yep if you just
like if you just like put it I'm not
even going to indent but yeah you know
yep yeah exactly so it's exactly that's
exactly what I was asking and so I guess
you're saying well we could totally do
that you could and that just gives you
this tree this way right yep which is a
first and then then a plus b comes next
and then we just keep attaching you know
little fronds that reach up as we keep
going right and of course again this is
right
sometimes this is right when precedence
is going
down okay and the key Insight is that
that's all you need to solve any problem
is you know what's right when precedence
is going up you know what's right when
precedence is going down now I don't
think these papers ever express this
this way but that's
maybe my contribution is just to like
think about it in a slightly wacky way
like this all right yep um okay so these
two things are all you need right so if
you do the recursive thing that's right
when precedence is increasing the loop
is right when precedence is decreasing
but you don't really you know it's not
that hard to put them together you might
think about like some highle thing that
shifts back and forth but no it's
actually very fluid so here is um code
that combines both of these things um
this is a recursive thing and again I
keep saying recursive but you could turn
it into a loop recursion just is a way
of using the programming languages stack
as a stack data structure right and so
if you want to make your own Loop
version of that you just make a stack of
your own um but I just for for
Simplicity and brevity I made it
recursive right
so um
here as long as we keep seeing operators
of increasing precedence we do the right
Leaning Tree and what that is is just as
a parameter now we're passing in the
left hand side which we did in the
previous version and that's that's part
of putting these together right and then
we passed down the Precedence which is
just how do how do you know it's
increasing well every time you get an
operator you look at the Precedence
right and the first call to this passes
like negative infinity or whatever
whatever your range of Precedence is
every time you get an operator you say
What's the the next precedence if it's
lower or equal um to what we have then
just pretend like we ran out of input
basically just return return that thing
right otherwise just do the thing we did
in the recursive version before where we
make the right Leaning Tree by parsing
another expression and keep going right
so as long as precedence goes up we make
a right leaning subtree right
now back here we have an outer loop like
the version that we just saw and
instead of in this version back here we
were parsing one binary node and that
gave us this instead of just parsing one
binary node we just say parse as many as
you want as long as it keeps going up
right and then come back around and
that's our new leftand
side and then just pass that in
again um and that's it this
is the entire code that handles oper at
precedence right and so you alluded to
like seeing small amounts of code before
that's what they look like yeah this is
like the first half of the Dragon book
yeah yeah like that's an exaggeration
but not really because
yeah like this is the only real problem
that you have when making a programming
language is to decide well when when
parsing a programming language yeah no
there's plenty of problems later but
when parsing stuff you just need to
decide you know what is what does the
input text actually mean there have to
be rules that determine what it means
and those rules need to be clear right
and there needs to be an implementation
of them and this this does that and so
we you know we did do a little bit of a
leap between this one and this one
because it's like we keep passing this
left tree through the loop and like what
does that mean right and by the way this
might at this point be substantially
different from what's in those
references because again I didn't really
read them I just figured it out but I
kind of feel like it has to be the same
thing
because it's roughly the what El you do
I remember there's a bunch of different
ways you can phrase this operation but
if that's what it is yeah yeah okay so
now um let's let's show an equation that
is not monotonically increasing or
decreasing right and and like how does
this work so here's one where we sort of
started doing our a greater than b right
this is the increasing but it's got a
plus e on the end right and so the right
answer for this is this you want to make
sure to do the times first which in this
case if we do the full parenthesis
version it looks like that and so if you
convert this to the tree just by that
rule of like can I Circle the sub tree
this is the right answer and that maybe
looks like a scary
tree but it's actually not scary because
it's it's two right leaning trees glued
together where this x here is just this
tree right and we already know how to
make these These are made by the stupid
Parson increasing precedence code right
so that's basically how this works is
um you know uh well I I Ste through
it let's uh let's see if I still
remember how to explain I basically went
through it literally every step and
maybe I should have actually put it in a
program and step through in the debugger
but I didn't so um let me let's go let's
go split screen
and uh we can keep the code up here okay
uh right and then over here so uh this
part when I say parse and then a number
here that's just a call to this parse
expression I
think um hold on or is it a call to the
probably the yeah I I named them both
starting with the word parse anyway so
we start out we parse a leaf right oh
yeah so we parse the leaf that's going
to be a we pass it into parse increas
precedence okay that's going to see the
greater than so I must mean this yeah
that's what I I was like it has to
because the other one doesn't build a
tree oh yeah this is recursive right so
so this this called a parse one parse
one just means calling this function
again recursively it could be an
iteration of a loop again don't don't
you know don't fixate on the recursion
part um parse one again makes a tree
like we were saying before we keep
making sub trees and waiting till later
right so we do that greater than we do
the Plus we do the times till now it
keeps going up so we're fine right when
we do D um hold on where's the let me
paste the original
equation um so we call parse three parse
3 sees
D um and then it sees a plus right but
the Precedence that we passed in was the
Precedence of times Which is higher so
you can't go down so we just returned D
instead of saying d uh plus anything
right so we the recursive version stops
here and gives you this tree
okay um and then this is just showing
how that tree gets built because we're
recursing back up right so we got the D
back we had c times something we had c
times parse three right the result of
parse 3 is D so we have C * d right and
then parse one was B plus the result of
parse
two uh yeah B plus the result of parse
two right and so on so we build this
tree now um this
subtree gets returned from here and then
the the node the node that we got back
is not equal to the left hand side that
we passed in so we continue that's our
new left hand side here this B
plus
wait that's right and and then you pass
it to like you parse the plus and call
parse
four
um you really there should be a parse
for above like in between these two sort
of
but I think okay hold on I I left out a
step
somewhere I left out a
step no you didn't because that's the
left you got back the left and then
you're going to call parse increasing
precedence passing that tree which is
going to
parse yes yes so you just left out a
label I left out yeah yeah yeah um The
Secret of why this works is um and and
this is an important change from the
earlier version you know in the early
versions of the parse binary tree it
would like call itself this is why
remember really early on I'm like I
don't remember why I put this one in
it's because of this because I wanted to
introduce a version where the the old
parse binary calls back to parse
expression instead of calling itself
because what actually makes this work is
every time you get back a new
subtree this Loop keeps trying from from
the Precedence that you use to start
parsing that sub tree right
right and uh and that's how you get this
right here this funny shape is you got
back this sub tree this greater then is
still waiting higher up it's like we we
parse that input but it's like on the
stack right
we haven't returned back to it yet so we
see this um and then what we came in
here with this Min
pre when we've got this is the
Precedence of the greater than right
because that's what our caller said you
know you have to
stop uh at any greater than or or
anything anything greater than the
greater than
that's right so um so here you know plus
again is higher precedence than greater
than so it's fine so we do our binary
tree then but you know instead of having
a leaf as the left hand side we have
this whole thing that we passed in and
that calls parse 4 which gets the E it's
there wasn't much left it was just the E
so then this returns that back and then
this Loop um loops around and uh there's
nothing new so we return this whole
thing here and then the collar attaches
that to the greater than right and so we
get this complex tree shape
um it's pretty simple like it's it's a
little bit complicated to think about in
the way that any tree operation is I
think in that like oh just step through
it and see and I don't expect this
explanation I expect a lot of people
would still be scratching their heads a
little bit um but if you just go through
a few cases it's like pretty obvious
what's going on right and this is this
is basically the whole problem right now
well why is it the whole problem what
about other stuff besides binary
operators right so like can see you have
like array
subscripts um this is actually easier
than a binary operator um it actually is
a an array subscript is a binary
operator because it's the thing you want
to subscript and then the the index
value um it's just got a little bit more
syntax and that actually makes it easier
because you don't have to worry about
what's on the right hand side of this
bracket it's like okay we just stop the
index here so the way that this work
Works in our code is we just treat the
left bracket as a binary operator in the
Precedence table just like anything else
right um we actually use the asky values
for most of these um there's a few you
know when when you have multi- character
operators there's no obvious asky value
so those don't but you know we just
literally have the asky value for this
um and that handles aray subscripts
um you know here's an example of a thing
another kind of thing that the tree
rewriter used to do that's handled natur
Naturally by this system is like if you
say s. a
subb right and you have some special
function that does even though array
subscript is pretty simple you might
have some modify like we have some weird
modifiers you might have or um but we
basically do a function that's like the
for Loop thing that I was talking about
where it's like oh if you see a bracket
just expect you know parse that parse an
expression and then expect a close
bracket it's very simple um but it's
like a a few lines of code that are
right there and um if you do that you
end up with
um
uh I don't have the wrong one but you
end up with s. a subb is sort of the
tree that you end up with again that's
why precedence matters here this is
meaningless if you don't know like what
this is like a struct and we're dotting
and there's an array element of the
struct and you can't evaluate this
without knowing the struct so it's a
terrible way way to have the tree right
you actually want this you want s. a
subscript B right and that's why you
need to fix the Precedence for this kind
of case you can do that either through
tree rewriting or through the thing that
I did here or I mean I guess we have to
talk about The Crafting interpreters one
at the end
um okay
so
um yeah I mean these are just this is
just to show that it matters what's the
thing on the left just like any math
operator right like a a a a struct
subscript operator has precedence just
like a math operator because you want
this text to turn into that but if you
just change this character to a plus you
want it to be different right no
surprise to anyone who's experienced but
just an
illustration
um yeah I mean this is just
uh in order to handle the close bracket
um this parse increasing precedence Loop
basically it's like look it do the same
thing make sure it's a higher precedence
than what we had and then like one way
you could do it which is what I actually
did is like look if that operator was
the left bracket just call this function
that also handles the right bracket
right again it's a small thing it could
be inline here but um you know otherwise
just maybe it's a binary operator so do
this right and you do that for
parentheses as well then or yeah yeah
yeah okay parentheses are very simple
parentheses just says call this parse
expression right
um with uh with again negative Infinity
for the Precedence because right because
you're restarting you're restarting yeah
it's like it's like it's in a black hole
in its own Universe right and then you
do that and then you come out right um
and then function calls are the same you
know they're syntactically they have a
little bit more to them but we talked
about the for loop it's the same thing
for a function call it's like oh I see
um I saw an expression right because it
could be an identifier but it could be
like d referencing an array of function
pointers or whatever right I saw an
expression and then an open pen so we're
going to start parsing a function and
then you know look for commas and and
look for expressions and then look for
the close so that's logically speaking
it's all handled the same way like
anytime you want to do a more a more um
let's say more rigid syntax than
something like binary operators or
something or a more elaborated syntax I
don't know but these all like the thing
about these programming languages
that I don't know if it's luck or
necessity or what but anytime we have
these more elaborate syntaxes there just
isn't really ambiguity that's not
handled by this like again you do the
function call and once you're in here
you're in parentheses and like you can't
believe lead into the outside world so
what are you going to do and wouldn't
the commas just be automatically handled
by operator precedence anyway depends on
if comma is an operator and C it is
right and so yes uh even if it wasn't
you could parse it as if it was using
this parser could you not yeah I mean
okay so there are a few different ways
you could do stuff like this um I'm
trying to remember if we do this for
commas I think we do like so so in in in
my language comma is not an operator
which leads me to to be motivated to
handle it differently um but in C you
have two choices about how you want to
parse this one is you could if comma was
very very low precedence which I believe
it is like if it was at the very bottom
of the Precedence table Yeah you could
like pass that in as the Min preck that
we were showing and then you'll you'll
stop at comma and then you parse the
comma right yeah um another thing you
could do which is something that I do
for other things I don't remember if I
do this for comma but in addition to
these two parameters I do have a third
parameter uh which is also in here which
is just like some control Flags about
what you're allowed to parse right now
and it's just like look are you allowed
to see an open brace here as the start
of an expression or or not right so like
in C you have open brace could be part
of a literal or it could be code and I
don't know you have a choice about how
to handle that right
but that I think by the time you have
those three parameters the left tree the
Min precedence and the control Flags
like you basically can do anything like
there's no you know um and it's much
more expressive and powerful than having
to fit it into some weird like stack
machine like from the Dragon book
so
um oh what was I going to say over here
oh your other option of how to do
this is to actually just Parts this as
one
expression and then again just say oh is
it a is it a binary operator that
happens to be comma okay that's the
first argument you have a little Loop
that like UNT trees it that way right um
You have that's the great thing about
programming is there's multiple ways to
solve problems um okay so I sort of
skipped over this thing about equal
precedents I talked about plus not
really mattering
um the official rule for this that you
will see in those papers is that um it
depends if it's left or right
associative right so if your operator's
left associative which most operators
are um there's really almost none that
are right associative someone someone in
a paper had or one of the blogs had the
example of an exponent operator which I
guess that makes sense that that's right
associative right y um I I don't have
that in my language C doesn't have it so
whatever but if you had that
then there's a few ways of of how to
handle it you could have an if statement
you could have an an extra because my
precedences are integer and I hope most
people's are um you could bias like when
you do this
comparison um where is it uh this one
right uh you could
add
um is it minus one or plus I don't want
to think about it but the point being
you could have a number that for most
operators is zero but for wrest
associative is one and that allows you
to continue in the loop right it would
have to be um minus one I guess uh or
plus one on this side right and that
would just
say uh keep stay in this loop as long as
it's the same precedence which is what
you want to do for right associative
operators um for left associative
operators um you want to do uh the left
leaning tree thing that that your Loop
would have produced right um
and again in my parser I don't think
about this rule at all because we have
no right associative operator so right
it's not even a thing yeah yeah yeah um
because it will always left associate by
default because of the way you're
passing the argument down and making
that decision yes you don't need to do
anything yeah yes and then that's
literally everything like and it's so
disappointing like on the one hand this
this information is out there in various
forms you can again you could follow the
links that I had earlier but like
there's just so much confusion around it
and so many
um like people pretend like it's science
or whatever but like what it really all
this really is all we are doing here is
saying it's almost tological it's like
look the
tree the tree is the parentheses so we
just need the tree to be the right shape
to be the parenthesis and how do you do
that
okay we need to compare precedences like
and I I guess it's a little bit clever
that it's not that much code but it's
just um it's staggering to
me how people make a big deal out of it
like I don't even know um I mean I guess
you know if you're newer at programming
this I'm sure this seems very
complicated maybe right but like if
you've ever shipped a commercial video
game like this is this is so simple
compared to so many of things we do
um yeah um do you so I the only thing
that I could think about is to talk
about The Crafting interpreters one um
unless you had other other topics or
questions yeah so
um I guess I'd like to just ask sort of
one follow-up question which you know I
could probably guess what the answer is
but yeah it would be
why do you need anything other than this
so it sounds like from what you said
that effectively the problem the reason
why you need something other than just a
loop that does exactly what you just
described to parse
everything is because of programming
constructs where the
symbols mean something different because
a previous symbol told you they would so
for example you gave you said for Loop
yeah I'm just trying to be concrete here
yes um so you see a four statement and
suddenly the meaning of semicolon kind
of changes like normally in C or C++ or
most languages you couldn't have a open
parentheses some stuff and then a
semicolon right because the semicolon is
a way of ending a line yeah and you're
ending a line in the middle of a for
statement which you know in en sorry in
the middle of of a par parenthetical you
wouldn't to do but because it's a for
statement that's not what that means so
I'm assuming
that uh let let me make a sort of bold
statement here being someone who doesn't
write parsers I'm just going off of what
you said
yeah would it be possible do you think
to write your entire compiler using just
that Loop and the only thing you would
do is have different precedence tables
based on that you switch when you saw
keywords like like is it really is is
really all of parsing just we do some
left and some right in alternating
because it seems like maybe it would
have to be since those are the only
trees you could produce or are there
actually things where it's like no you
need to actually custom parse some
things not just because it's easier to
write it that way and to report errors
which mean or you know or is it
basically programming languages no they
just don't have things that couldn't be
pared this way in general so in this
case you would make semicolon a really
low
yeah precedence operator you still have
the weirdness where
um you have a few weirdnesses with
semicolon specifically right so in the
four Loop case you're talking about it
acts like an operator because there
isn't one on the right although I
believe you could optionally put one
right but typic you're allowed not to
right which is weird right
um but with statements you're not
allowed to not put one on the last
statement but you you are allowed to put
five in a row with nothing in between
and so like your operator your normal
operator
parsing would have to add complexity to
deal with that anyway and so when you're
talking about things this
simple it's a substantial amount of
complexity so relative to the the base
and so I don't know that I would
ever seriously try to do it that way but
it might be a fun thing
um the thing so so just for context for
people you know we've sort of been
focusing on this like parse expression
is like an expression in a programming
language is is just like one of the
fundamental units that could be in most
places right I I don't know if there's a
better a better explanation than that
probably there is probably the Dragon
book has a 17-page explanation of
expression is that nobody understands um
but uh you know usually you at least in
a SE like language you'll have one
higher level thing which is like
statement level which would handle the
semicolon right and there are things
that are statements that are not
expressions like a a declaration of a
variable is a statement but you can't
have it down in the middle of stuff
right and so um you already tend to
naturally make this hierarchy of
functions that parse specific things and
I would
say that is actually the attraction of
this kind of parsing which again I'll
say recursive dissent because that's the
name that people know but like it's not
that
complicated like calling functions is a
thing that we do it's like not rocket
science to call functions and that's all
we're talking about so you have a
function that parses a statement and
that's just very clear right I mean
sometimes things get messy when you make
them complicated but at at its core
everything is laid out right there and
you see it right and that's very good
it's very underrated actually um
so the thing that you're talking about
would obfuscate that to some degree I
think oh yeah it wouldn't probably be
good for error reporting as we talked
about right because we're understanding
the code honestly it's gonna be like
operator president error it's like the
only error in the programming L dude
back when I was in college like shipping
GCC or
whatever still would tell you shift
reduce error or whatever when you got a
sytax error yeah shift
reduce [ __ ] awesome you know and
you're like dude I don't care how you
implemented the parser
like so bad so bad okay um let's talk
about this let me see if I can find the
the crafting interpreters thing I did
say it's very slow and you shouldn't do
it this is true I don't wish to bag on
it too hard though because it's also um
kind of awesome okay it's kind of
awesome okay okay um all right so before
before we go look at this one let's go
back and remember sort of the property
that makes this work for weird arbitrary
tree shapes is that this Loop here keeps
trying from the earlier precedence right
we keep parsing right leaning trees and
then gluing them on but it's like this
Loop is like the thing that makes it
work right okay so now I'm hoping I
actually had the paper copy of crafting
interpreters this is the online I don't
know if it's the same uh but it was
chapter six
in my copy so they're they talk about
BNF grammars and stuff which I wouldn't
encourage you here's here's the
explanation of the precedent problem um
again I didn't really read this either I
skimmed it okay recursive descent
parsing
um he's first parsing some stuff made
all out of equal signs so the precedent
that's like our plus sign
example
um okay now
I had to read this like five times to
understand what was going on because
it's like can this be made any bigger
it's kind of hard to read yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah um it's it's pretty
stealth how okay so like the Precedence
explanation starts here and like I read
it and I was like where's the pre I
don't where's the Precedence right and
okay I just want to encourage
people there's a class of explanation
that you read it and it seems like you
get it but if you think about it you
realize you really don't get it and
because I had just worked on this
problem I read this
text and I was like dude I just
implemented a parser that does correct
precedence for our Corpus of 700 tests
and our shipping game that's 300,000
lines long I should understand this and
I don't I had to like step through it to
understand so I I guess part of that
though
just speaks to the difficulty of
explaining Concepts in text sometimes
right but okay
so somewhere up
here he there's a couple of sentences I
don't even know if I'm going to find
it
um yeah it's all in Java by the way have
fun with that um I can't find it okay
we'll just look at the code like this is
how stealth it is so what what happens
is you implement a bunch of functions
instead of one function for a binary
operator like I had you group your
operators into precedence level C does
this there's like a table of what
operator at what precedence and so for
each precedence level you make a
separate function it's sort of like Comm
where you have to make a separate class
for every button or whatever right yeah
okay but this is also what's awesome
about it right okay so minus and plus in
this toy language that they're parsing
are the lowest I I guess the double
equals is um comparison so it starts
actually up here so comparison says it's
got a while loop remember I said the
while loop is the Workhorse that makes
this work right while the Precedence is
going to be equal or higher you keep
doing the thing right so here we say
this is just parsing and it where does
he call
comparison I don't know anyway this is
the equivalent of our parse expression
you would enter here and okay maybe an
expression is a comparison operator if
it
is uh well we have something on the left
right that we parsed just like the the
version that you were talking about so
we pars the thing on the left first
actually then we look for the comparison
operator if it's one of these then um
parse a thing on the right and then make
a binary tree just like I was saying
okay the weird stealth magic is okay
well you'll note this isn't comparison
right it's a thing called term yeah
what's term term is this thing down here
that's like oh higher precedence
operators right maybe it's not one of
these maybe it's a minus or a plus right
so yeah do this right okay but what's on
the left because we have to pass the
left in it's Factor what's factor it's
this thing down here factor is like
maybe its times are divide right yep and
okay may but maybe it's a operator right
um or maybe it's primary and primary is
what I was calling Leaf of the tree
um I didn't like the word primary
because so he has simple stuff here plus
this but like all the for Loop and
whatever that we're talking about are
essentially they're sort of tree leaves
relative to everything else except they
have complex structure inside right
again they're like a black hole or
whatever yep
so this actually works and I had to
convince myself that this works again by
taking some of my test cases and like
stepping through but it literally does
do the right thing it's as if you took
any notion of press you got rid of all
the data in the solution that I talked
about and you baked it completely into
code now the reason I am saying please
do not do this is the following imagine
your input is the number three or
whatever it's time to pars a three yeah
which is common or the name of a
variable like these are all over your
program okay what do you have to
do to find out that it's three you're
like maybe it's greater than right maybe
it's maybe maybe and then and then you
come down here right yeah um and
so it's not it's not very efficient
firstly and then
secondly the thing is it's not very
fluid with respect to if you're working
on a language and you're adding new
things where does this go oh maybe this
should be higher precedence than this
thing no let me move it down here this
is kind of inflexible in that way and
and maybe easy to make copy pasta errors
or whatever right because you have to
keep you have to keep making all these
functions and then who calls who has to
change around anytime you change a
precedence
but I give it the gold star for
like the most hardcoded baked down
implement M mentation right um yeah you
can type it in entirely in just a top
down style without needing a table or
anything or anything yeah like hey my
embedded CPU does this it uses zero
bytes of memory
um I think on an embedded CPU you
probably really wouldn't want this but
okay well yeah I don't know um somebody
somebody in chat was saying he talks
more about precedence later and maybe
miss that part but like I said I missed
most of this part like I had to read
this like several times before I
understood what it was doing because it
just looks
like it just looks like redundant
recursive function declarations for
binary operators and it's like okay it
is that but the hierarchy of the
functions does the work put put in terms
of the way that you explained it with
the like we need to be able to build
left leaning trees and right leaning
trees and then we need to inter leave
them as as necessary yeah essentially
what he has done here is just said
well I am going to make the recursive
call part build one side of one lean and
I'm going to make the while loop build
the other lean and because each step can
do both we now have the ability to make
left leaning and right leaning inter
leave done yeah and we have solved the
problem right another way to say this
for people is instead of passing like
the minimum precedence as a parameter
it's like you made a bunch of copies of
the function and you put the name of
another function is essentially the
minimum precedence of what you're
allowed to post now right well stated
yes it's almost like you had tempate you
had like template like uh uh you know
less than Min pre clo you know close and
you just made an instance of every
different operator precedence as a
function yeah and call it yeah don't do
that I don't recommend that again Robert
nrom May recommend it he may not I don't
know why again I know he knows the other
thing because he wrote a blog post
explaining it 10 years before this so
this is not to bag on the author of this
in any way it's just I would
not if someone working for me wrote this
we would have a conversation you know
that's all I'm saying um I see but maybe
it's easier to understand I don't know I
don't know people
people can tell me if they find this
version easier than the the Min pre
version um I don't know but that's it
that was um so I just wanted to say you
know again I don't think any of this
information is super new because there's
people out there who know these facts
it's
just again when I went to go read
things like when you go read a source of
technical
knowledge these days you really really
have to be asking yourself how much you
should trust it right that was less true
before although as we know we we talked
about some examples that stretches way
back into time um and
so you know the again the problem when
you go trying to read about this stuff
is you don't know what to trust and if I
don't know that I should trust something
maybe there's a personality difference
between us if I don't know that I should
trust something like my energy
investment in figuring out if I should
trust it
depends on how many other options I have
right it's like if this is my only
option and I don't know how trustworthy
it is what else am I going to do I'm
going to figure it out I'm going to
study this description and try to
understand how it works um if you have
an entire internet full of other stuff
I'll just search for something else and
like there's just so much noise is the
problem and um it's really so simple and
so I just want to try to signal boost a
little bit I mean that's the reason why
I wanted to make it a public stream is
we could put it on YouTube next to the
other thing and it's a nice book end to
that question that we had about how to
do precedence and I was like oh just
write some code it's like okay well no
this is you would actually call this an
algorithm yeah um whereas the thing that
I used to do is not even really an Al I
mean you would the way that people use
the algorithm the word algorithm these
days everything is an algorithm but the
the thing I did before was like look
just write algorith but not the
algorithm which of course is something
totally different yes of course
um anyway I was just I was also hyped
that it was so simple and so easy to
figure it out so I was like hey let's
just do a little talk and go through I
would also say that like it's uh it's
good I I think your explanation is good
as well for people who want to
understand so so shunting yard is a good
example of a literal algorithm like here
is a very this is defin it's an
algorithm with with a name and
everything yes uh and you can understand
it much better once you've walked
through it the way you have because as
you pointed out it's basically just
doing the same thing but it does it it
explains it in terms of just if you just
have a stack instead of having an actual
recursive call of some kind uh and stuff
like that so it's like it's just helpful
to understand as well to have more
explanations more explanations are
better because there are like you said a
bunch of people who have done something
like this but it's not always easy to
understand why their thing works or what
it's
doing um but it's always doing this
basically I
mean the the output the correct output
is predetermined right yes and so
therefore
um I mean there's there's some freedom
in in what the implementation could be
obviously we just looked at this other
one but like it's kind of constrained by
how complex could the mapping possibly
be right like at some point if your
implementation is so complex you must be
doing a lot of extra stuff that could be
simplified away because the input is not
that complicated and the output is not
that complicated it's just like yeah and
I
just I don't understand why this has
been made so hard I mean I'm frustrated
because like look dude my hobby in
college was making toy programming
languages at first I would do
um uh you know parser generator kind of
stuff Yak yeah like I made like 11 or 12
of these right and then I very quickly
graduated to like yeah this actually
sucks if you use it and you you know
what you can write on your own so I very
by the end of that process was fully on
the write your own Lex gloyer and parser
train um however I actually don't
remember what I did for press back then
it's weird I know I did
something um because the stuff worked
and it's very frustrating to program in
a language that doesn't have that has an
infixed notation and no precedence but I
I don't remember and I don't have any of
that code I don't think you've got lurp
what did you do in there can we rewrite
lurp was weird because I
didn't yeah I could go look um but like
I maybe wasn't concerned with this kind
of thing yet anyway because I was more I
was more doing this weird like database
as a primitive thing and yeah I don't
know
I I mean it certainly had a alexir and a
parser in it and so I could go dig that
up but yeah I don't have any of my
college day code around so I wonder what
I
did
um but yeah it's just like how do I go
this long and not understand something
so simple and maybe it's my fault maybe
I'm dumb but I don't think so I think
like even like you know you go on hacker
so this thing one one name for this I
think is a pratt parser which I mean I'm
conflicted about names like that in
general because you know it's because of
this original paper that like I don't
understand but
um you know give credit where credit is
due but also I feel like when you name
stuff you make it sound complicated and
then you go on Hacker News and there's
people talking about how Pratt parser
combat ators are the future of computers
or whatever and you're just like oh my
God guys um like they're like new
advances in uh reverse frobin or
whatever and you're like what's that and
you're like oh it's we we've almost got
this new like theoretical parser to to
run at one character per second of of
input or whatever and you're just you're
kind of your head explodes about why
they are still like looking at this
stuff but
yeah yeah exactly
we throw an exception per character yeah
and so yeah I can understand the
exacerbation but to be fair that happens
in literally everything like there are
people rat huling in theoretical stuff
for everything uh someone says which
find sometimes they find something
someone says LOL but the book explains
that in the next part let's just look
because again my goal here is not is not
to
denigrate anything um
but I mean I I read the thing and it
sounded like I had gotten to the end of
the so recursive Des this is all the
stuff we looked at Sy and then it talks
about syntax errors and I was like okay
parsing must be done um do you mean yeah
that seems like the end yeah do you mean
part seven wiring up the
parser aor
handling delete the blah blah blah
design note logic versus
history should we put where okay
yeah so he's talking about that which I
probably agree with
um okay so this is like a a side note
about
precedence no this is a side note about
backward compatibility yeah this is not
really about that so do they mean part
seven next evaluating expressions no
that because that's iterating over the
tree and like chat what are you talking
about be more specific
chat oh wait wait wait wait there's okay
someone has given me a specific link yes
you needed we needed chat to be more
specific where the link isn't opening
chapter 17 oh so by the next part you
mean chapter 17 I mean I I think that's
fine again like maybe the advanced stuff
is at the end if you consider that but
that's not that I would yeah I would say
no because if if that's what you were
handed as your first explanation though
yeah right like like it's important to
explain it clearly the first time that
that's kind of what we're talking about
like obviously anyone who becomes an
expert in parsers will know about Pratt
parsers or whatever else you want to
call this sort of stuff because you'll
study the problem with ton the point is
if you're someone who doesn't want to
become an expert in parsers you just
want to write a parser the first
explanation should explain this that's
that's the whole point of this whole
thing the Dragon book for all I know
might have a PR parser mentioned in some
exercise to the reader I almost
guarantee they do but but they don't you
know that's not the problem the problem
is not that that the information doesn't
exist it's that it's not presented as
the first way to understand it is that
you have left and right leaning trees
and you're trying to inter leave them
which is the which is the critical part
right yeah I'm looking in the P section
really fast Pratt VR 189 to 90 yeah so
they mention it for like one page yeah
in the Dragon book yep yeah and it's
like yeah in the references for chapter
3 so they don't even really talk about
the algorithm it's like references okay
um so this is if this is about parsing
it's misleading because it's called
compiling expressions and that to me
says like backend
stuff this is definitely back in but
there was a thing that said side note
it's just part okay Pratt parsers are a
sort of oral Trad ition no compiler or
language book I've read teaches
them okay so so he's talking about that
paper here it's the most elegant way I
know to parse why are we parsing
Expressions again in section 17 that's
really weird no one would know to even
look at this if you were just building a
parser because you wouldn't be reading
this part I mean I guess you know so I'm
using it as a reference right but if
you're using it as a learning book you
read it differently and you probably
read the whole thing so I don't know no
okay no I object I object again because
this is exactly what happens with the
Dragon book you read the parsing part
and you go wow this is really confusing
you may never get to the compiling part
like you have to teach the parsing well
because without a like solid
understanding of how to build a parser
and keep that simple they're they're
never going to get to the part where
they like you know do optimization
passes or whatever else right so like no
this is the same problem as the Dragon
book again yeah I mean I don't I don't
understand the motivation behind doing
this later maybe we should ask him um
yeah it it seems weird to me because
he's like oh now we're I guess so it's
called crafting interpreters right and
an interpreter is a lighter weight thing
than a compiler where you have some
other program that's the runtime
typically you might even look just at
the tree and like run plus by saying oh
I'm visiting the binary tree and this
node is plus and so I'm going to add a
and b or whatever right and then
compilers are when you take that several
steps further such that you can create a
program that could run on its own
without something else running it right
that's the difference between an
interpreter and a compiler um I don't
know why that like he's acting here
like that causes you to change the
parsing which it doesn't yeah it's very
strange the parsing the method of
parsing is orthogonal so I have to
believe that this is more incidental
like he want he felt like that was more
advanced and wanted to leave it till
later Poss
it's just weird I don't I don't get it
okay
um but yeah this is
mostly parsing token what why are we
here again it's so weird to redo this
like you'd think that this would have
been in the first part where about about
parsing maybe this was going to be a
second book or something and it wasn't
long enough maybe or maybe maybe this
book is more of just a collection of
things and that got Loosely reorganized
and it wasn't ever designed as a book
like I I reshuffled my blog posts or
whatever you know sometimes that can
happen Okay parsing prefix expressions
parsers for to parenthesis for
grouping I still don't really I mean I'm
skimming again obviously but I still
don't see the actual okay here we go
here we go this is the actual part that
explains it it's yeah two-thirds of the
way down sections 17 about a compiler
inste 17.5 I mean it's good it again
this is good information I'm glad it's
I'm glad it's here I just don't quite
understand don't understand the order of
the information and again it need to get
moved up yeah it's not it's not temporal
in the order he learned it or anything
because he wrote that blog 10 years
before this so he knew this the whole
time
um so he's here he's in leaving parsing
with output which again it's a fun stunt
but like you don't want to do that once
you're compiler exceeds a
certain complexity but I mean for
teaching I guess it's it's fun to show
how simple it could be to right to emit
code right
um all
right there's a precedence table pre
none for all these
things I don't
know
um get
rule
okay yeah so he's broken it into a
couple of functions here
but
um and I
don't I don't know if these definitions
are above or below Advance might be
eating a token
oh God he's broken these into separate
functions that you
return because Java all right I I'm not
gonna understand this yeah yeah but so
he returns a function from get
rule I I don't know I don't know get
rule is
later this looks more complicated at
than it needs to be honestly but okay
but but he does talk about it and
reference it I don't I can't evaluate
just from a skim how good I think the
explanation is but the information is
there and but once again it's not it
doesn't look like it's explaining it in
terms of like I really liked your
explanation of it in terms of like look
we know that it's either going to be one
a tree that goes this way or a tree that
goes that way and all we have to do is
like alternate between those to get the
right thing here we go that's a much
easier way to understand how these
algorithms work work and so again I
would say that needs to be kind of front
and center I think in an explanation
because a lot of times these things are
implicit like they don't really like say
what actually needs to happen for the
algorithm and it leaves you wondering
what the algorithms actually does well
that's that's my big thing that's my
beef about a lot of things like
technical writing generally this book by
the way is sort of this book is I I do
agree that I don't while skimming see
and the Deep explanation that I would
like but maybe it's there and I just
maybe we spend some more time with it
yeah not a criticism of this at all but
more like when you read some of these
computer science papers right there's
like an academic computer science voice
that people have learned to write in
that is not very much like the voice of
the great computer science papers by the
way so right you know think about that
but it's it's a voice that involves
trying to sound smart but also not
explaining things too much and
especially not explaining um the
important part the the reason you would
do something and the context and when
would you do this and and when might it
be a better idea to do something else
right and like all of those that's the
real information like the algorithm like
if you have enough context and
understanding of the problem usually
algorithms are not that hard especially
if you have like a hint at what it is um
but like we we seem to have all this
writing that's the opposite and that's
what you know there was this tweet that
I deleted because I didn't want to
harass people accidentally but it was
about that before about that
probabilistic algorithm book before you
mention that tweet you should point out
that like this thankfully this crafting
interpreters page seems to have be
written in a much yes nicer fashion
which is nice like if you look at just
what's on the screen right now that's
very human readable right like no one's
going to be like what the heck is he
talking about they're they're like oh I
get it right like okay yeah see what
he's saying here so that's very
refreshing as well oh absolutely all in
favor if you're ever going to explain
something make it more like this and
less like whatever random computer
science paper the gjk paper that's the
ultimate reference of all time just read
the gjk paper and if your paper sounds
anything like that delete the entire
latch file and make a new one
yeah
um yeah okay so the information's in
there
someone says Java is asked walk interp
and C part is bite code inter turp I
don't know what c part means I guess
this is in C so they're redoing stuff in
C I don't know what Java looks like but
this looks like C to me so yeah um
anyway yeah the end I think we're out of
stuff to talk about but it's just yes I
wanted to do my part to signal boost
several things one this is very simple
don't first of all if you understand it
don't get all high and mighty and try to
confuse other people about it because
it's actually pretty simple yep
two what do we do about this cultural
problem that we have where if something
as simple as this still despite these
other people having done what they can
to publicize it is still not understood
by many people right what about the
things that are actually more
complicated right what about those
um I don't know but uh I mean I think
it's a fitness function problem right
like currently there is no reinforcement
function for someone else was able to
understand it in fact it's somewhat the
opposite like for academic stuff it's
probably easier to generate more papers
the less number of people understand
what you're talking about because
they're much less likely to reject it
from a journal if they don't really know
what you said exactly right like like if
you understand something you might
realize it's not new yes but if you
don't understand something and it just
kind of sounds like it's roughly
something then you'll be like oh yeah
you should publish that right or
whatever so I assume that part of the
problem is that if literally just
getting papers published is your Fitness
function you're kind of it this is what
happened so you just have to stop that
like the whole idea of like peer rreview
journals and all that that has to go
away that was a very bad idea it should
never have happened and what you should
be doing is like hey if a particular
publication is able to actually have
other people be able to go do something
with it that is the actual Fitness
function and how do we get there how do
we get more towards that right yeah I
agree with that I I think one other
thing that happens is a lot of so-called
algorithms
right like especially as you get more
applied and these papers that claim
performance wins and stuff which are
usually almost never real
um garbage collection is faster than man
manual memory management yeah or or even
our tweak on garbage collection improves
it by 13% and it it doesn't really right
and it also by the way has all these
pathological cases and stuff and inputs
we we just wanted to get this paper out
so we didn't really think about this
other thing right and it's like these
papers are full of that stuff and the
more you understand what they're
actually saying
the more you see those holes right
whereas if you if you don't really
understand the algorithm and you're just
like oh yeah yeah looks good right
um same thing right that that feeds into
that paper Fitness function thing you
were talking about um and from a
slightly different direction so yeah oh
dude I just I have so much beef about
computer science papers that claim
performance improvements it's been it's
been sadness every time yeah there's
there's a lot of issues with that most
computer science papers don't know how
to measure things so they're very
suspicious usually yeah um but yeah yeah
all right so we we have to bring back
the meme because yeah bring back the
meme this is what the people want this
is what the people want this is all so
the only takeaway that you really need
from from this stream is this meme yes
this is what this is about the entire
intellectual content of this stream
honestly can I make one can I make one
change to this meme to make it even more
awesome yes can the dude in the cloak
say that's left
sometimes that might be too smart but
let's let's do it let's here we go so is
that that makes it more specific to
parsing this particular parsing we are
we are a prompt
service cuz then it's like almost
impossible to even understand the meeme
unless you've seen this
stream because it won't make any sense
otherwise so do we want to modify
this or I think that was fine I'll put a
one must use ler one
generator with flex and
hjs with
them I mean there was a thing like uh
this is my only suggestion there that's
probably what you should put but I
remember the red dragon edition of the
book having some garbage on the front
like lr1 parser generator and syntax
directed translation can you can you
just copy what it said and stick it at
the top there because that is pretty
close to perfect as well okay okay um
syntax directed translation to defeat
the complexity of compiler design that's
literally what it says it says Okay so
the dragon this is the new version but
it's in principle it's a it's like when
Disney remakes The Lion King in live
action so all the elements of the scene
are the same um the dragon is wearing a
shirt that says complexity of compiler
design and the sword you can't really
see it but the sword is the sword of ler
parser generator you got to get that in
there and the shield of syntax directed
translation right yes all of which is
[ __ ] the one that isn't the one
phrase on here that isn't [ __ ] is
complexity of compiler design which is
true uh which is true but parsing isn't
the complicated part it's the rest of it
that's hard
so
uh syntax directed translation
with ler parser
generator yes it might be a little small
but yeah
well what can you do what can you memes
are this is the complexity of memes all
right I don't know I think this is as
high r as it goes yep all right see we
are we are a full service shop here
um yeah okay very low res oh it went off
the
top no no didn't oh I can't see it I
can't see the top of the meme am I uh so
my my OBS may not be oh okay okay no it
is it is maybe it's Google is not
showing you it could be Google is
Googling it as long as as it's visible
in the real meme I'm fine with it oh now
I can see it it was just the zoom I
guess
was making me not see it well the zoom
in yeah was cutting off the bottom for
me so ah okay
yeah okay
so that's
great thanks everybody um we could do
questions or something if you want to
hang out otherwise that's that's all I
want to talk about totally up to you
does anyone have intelligent questions
that is worth the time of Casey mtori
when he could be
off making new things for his
substack gallivanting yeah or
gallivanting or doing both of those
things simultaneously serious
questions oh someone is saying the
crafting interpreter book was in two
parts part one was in Java and part two
was in C and so maybe that corresponds
to The Interpreter and compiler Parts
but but then online it's all smooshed
together now that makes more sense I do
think it it feels like it that when we
were looking at it I was like this kind
of feels like a thing that was like it
was written in various ways and then you
know assembled and that kind of thing
always has some rough edges there like
Mike AB br's books were that way right
like they were like hey these were
series of Articles and then we kind of
reworked them for a book and whatever so
you kind of get a there's a little bit
of things where it's like wait why is
this here or in this spot and it's like
well you know yeah we're not going to
rewrite the entire thing to make it flow
correctly so
yes so here's a question um are
parenthesized expressions ever done in
parse Leaf in my example um so we did
sort of skip I
mean it's essentially the same as some
of these other cases we talked about of
more complex syntax it's actually it's
essentially the same as the for Loop
right so here's the
thing
um when you when you
parse when you're going to par an
expression let me I've got so many
versions of this function yeah like when
you're going to parse an expression um
you know you parse a leaf here and parse
Leaf I talked about in the very
beginning and just ignored it after
because it's like it's not the point but
when you're here what this is is just
looking at the next token and deciding
what is your value and if instead of a
three you see an open parentheses
then right here you just say if it's an
open parentheses return it's not really
a leaf because it's a sub expression but
you just go in right now the way that I
do un operators I skipped over uni
operators because it's like it's not
it's not really worth bothering but I
just handle them here as well I just say
if this is a un operator then
call the
uh call the parse expression with the
Precedence of that Unity operator
and there you go oh that is one
interesting change or difference between
the old version of the parser and the
new one besides getting rid of the tree
changing code um is before I you know I
had unit operator precedences for some
reason although they didn't really do
anything um and I had binary operator
precedences but they weren't even on the
same scale because they didn't likea
right so you unified them yes um and so
now they're like they're on the same you
know ruler and so when you're doing
things this generally if you don't pass
in the correct precedence from here
you'll mess up your your un versus
binary precedence but but basically
things either go here or in the parse
binary and it's like your entire grammar
you
know
okay what about parsing each binary
operator along with its right operand
and then just inserting that where it
fits and then link
um isn't that sort of what this is
doing past
bin uh parse un okay while token is
binary op parse
uny this is sort of like the tree
changing thing I was talking about this
is like a very compact version of it
because you're parsing it and then
you're like changing the links right if
I'm reading this
correctly I mean yeah so so hybrid
approaches between these two things I
think could work I'm not sure why you
would do
that
um I'm not thinking that hard about like
you're obviously you're starting at the
root sorry go ahead well it's
like
I don't know maybe this is just another
way of writing the same Loop but with it
is like basically this is this is the
unrec kursiv version of the thing right
you okay you keep building right leaning
trees or I should say you keep using the
right slot yeah you walk down the right
side until you need to walk down the
left side but the the only thing that
suss so I guess when this says part un I
was assuming that that meant like a un
operator or a leaf but I guess it means
an increasing precedence run like I was
talking about because otherwise why
would you ever need to cursor more than
one step or whatever you know that's
that's what's confusing me about this
um I don't know anyway um why not do it
this way I mean sure like if this works
that's great it's not really in
principle different um the you know the
the core idea again to to put it in the
bell curve meme way the core idea was
just that you know the default tree
making that you would do is Right In
some cases already and then just use
that to to construct the thing right I
would say there's one reason like again
I don't write parsers so I'm just going
off of what I've heard so far but yeah
one thing that I that doesn't look great
about this is effectively this gets
worse the more you have to do that inner
while loop so that's very sus I would
never do that right right so like in in
the one that John wrote Because You're
Building it kind of in order from the
bottom up you don't have that problem
you're always just going to the right or
going to the left and you're just doing
one step yeah or ever yeah this
version's like well now every time I get
a new one in I have to chase down to
find where I would have been when I
inserted it in John's version so it's
kind of it by flipping those two it
feels worse like it feels like this is
going to be like an N squ kind of a
thing that could happen if you construct
a adversarial input sort of thing I
could be wrong about honestly my my
brain's tired so I'm not thinking that
hard about it but um that's my only
thought does that yeah I mean this this
while loop I don't like how that looks
which I think is a summary of what you
just said um yeah the thing here's a
thing another thing about computer
school is they teach you to make trees
all the time and that navigating trees
is cool and fun um trees are really bad
and I want to at some point try to
figure out a way to make a version of
our compiler that does not use trees
it's difficult because they are in
principle trees in the sense that like
any recursive data structure is kind of
a tree sort of I guess because you're
referring to some other part that may be
small or it may be quite large um I
assume that
rpn kind of the existence of rpn means
somewhat implicitly that Expressions
anyway never need to be represented as a
tree you can just do them right like
like you you could easily make a
compiler if only it only ever dealt with
Expressions you would never have to have
a tree to get the right answer anyway
you might want a tree for other reasons
yes yes um so anyway the the thing about
like trees are bad for two reasons and I
think we talked about this a little bit
before maybe but all my experience since
then keeps like if I had time I wish I
had time to think about it right um the
nodes are really big like the tree for
this thing or just's take something
simpler like this is like node for the
equal node for this node for this node
for the UN operator maybe we don't have
statement nodes but some people would
and like it's like five nodes and they
all have like the probably the base node
that describes where they are in the
program so you can do error reporting
and all that and like probably some
stuff that helps link it to the later
result results of compilation right and
so like I don't know how big our bass
note is but it's like 100 bytes I don't
know it's like it's stupid right and so
imagine this was 500 characters long
instead of like 12 or whatever it is 11
um let me actually count 48 9 10 12 I
got it right so so that's a factor of 50
bigger than your Source text and that's
kind of dumb it just is yeah um and
I mean Casey probably knows like I'm I'm
not the most hardcore person about
optimization because I'm I more prefer
making functionality work but like I
don't do stupid slow crap and I don't
make things way bigger than they need to
be if it's important and like this is
really important because we instantiate
like millions of these nodes right and I
just it's hard to make them smaller
while it still I mean there's things I
could do to reduce a small number of
bites at great effort right right and
so yeah I just want to re-envision it at
some point as something that doesn't use
trees so the other thing about trees is
like this looks like a cheap operation
right but you're going to things that
might be distant in memory now that's
less bad here in the middle of a parser
because you probably just parsed this
stuff recently and if your allocator is
not like returning an address that's
like red mod size of and address space
you know then um that probably has
better Behavior right if it gives you
nodes that are next to each other but
you're still I mean it's still N squared
right it's N squared in the length of an
expression am I wrong about that chat
like like the the the main problem I see
with doing it backwards like this is
just that it's end squared unless I'm
misreading you maybe I can't see the
chat right now
so I don't know what they think but
that's my gut feeling is that like you
wouldn't do it this way because it's s
squared for no reason like no real
benefit if there was a benefit to it
maybe you'd say well I'll eat the nend
squared because you know I know that my
language you know I'm not trying to make
a language where you can have
Expressions that are you know a thousand
elements long or something which is fine
but you know it seems like a bad
decision yeah unless you got something
from it there there's something
someone's saying that I want to address
about this because this is a
common uh people who know a little bit
of optimization stuff modern things say
this and I want to push back on it just
just again to spread the the knowledge
so someone is saying someone said hey
allocating every time you want to create
a node we'll slow everything down and
someone else is saying you're Assuming
he's doing Malik every time he could
just be doing bump allocation and
actually I don't see the rest of the
context of the conversation because
there's a lot going on so maybe that
wasn't directly in reference to this but
if what is meant is it's not that bad to
do this or even make a tree because
you're not actually calling Malik it's
like okay yes it's good that you're not
calling Malo for every node that's great
that is a good step to take to make your
program faster it does not really
fundamentally solve certain classes of
problems you're still visiting memory
that may not be next to each other
because the reason you have a tree by
the
way right in the start we were all doing
left leaning trees and right leaning
trees which are pretty linear and so if
you have something like that that's
really long and it's all allocated in
memory from the leaf up or the root down
or whatever um actually in our case that
wouldn't have been true cuz like the the
left child was allocated and then we did
all the sub stuff and then we came back
like things may not end up being very
close to each other in memory actually
depending on the size of the tree but
the whole reason you have a tree is
because the shapes can get more complex
and then you navigate that more complex
shape and anytime you navigate a more
complex shape than that you you're
Crossing like any link between nodes is
a link between things that may be
getting further and further apart in
time right and
so on the one hand maybe that's a
fundamental part of the
problem but on the other hand you don't
want to do it more than you have to and
this looks like more than you have to to
me right that's what well could we can
we bring up the um a tangential that can
we bring up the meme
again okay which one version one or
version two version it doesn't matter
because I just need I just need the
visual reference
okay yeah so uh the other thing that you
could think about with this Meme here is
that
like uh on the the the guy who on the
left would be saying like just call
malok uh and then the guy in the middle
would be like you could be using a bump
allocator right yeah yeah uh and then
the guy on the right is like but what
about the page faults because actually
when you parse something like this even
if you're using a bump allocator if your
nodes are all huge you will page fault
all over the place and it's bad right
like there's compilers have this really
bad uh problem that a lot of programs
don't have uh which is that at startup
they don't have any memory because why
would they right you're just cold
calling them off of the command line
this is just how we have unfortunately
designed the execution environment of
modern Computing not much you can do
about it people expect to be able to
call a compiler for command line when
you do that the compiler doesn't have
any memory provisioned and so extra bite
you use is like well I should say every
extra 4K you use on something like
Windows is another page fault waiting to
happen which slows down the runtime of
your parser so you actually do care
about the size of things even if you're
using a bump allocator and think you're
not paying very much for allocation you
probably actually are in this particular
case yeah I told Casey this before um
and I think it sparked some of the
experiments he did but um it did
actually last time we measured it which
was a while ago and we haven't measured
it again since then but like 12% of our
runtime was just getting memory from the
operating system like it was a lot you
know like 12% when you're trying to
speed something up if you could make it
12% faster you're really happy if it's
already fast yeah if it was already a
reasonable program yeah yeah and and so
yeah it's just these things are problems
yeah uh someone says in a compiler I'm
working on I noticed in my code that I
only do depth first reverse
so I just linearized the tree into an
array of nodes in depth first order um
that's what you do too John isn't it
sort of in your compiler um kind of yeah
okay I
mean I still have the nodes I still have
the tree structure and sometimes I need
to ask what's the child doing right now
but I do I do linearize the nodes it's
for a little bit of a different purpose
which um which is about being able to
stop compilation and resume you know
because an identifier isn't ready or
something um you know now that
said the thing I've been thinking lately
is I do that I actually I used to do it
just by literally linearizing the nodes
like having a big array of all the
pointers and then then then I was
like you know that's kind of maybe too
dumb and you can imagine pathological
cases where you just allocate a giant
ass array that is not helpful so I went
to something that's a little bit more of
like a stack thing where you push
something on and then it expands its
children onto the stack and then you
visit them so it has a much smaller
memory footprint and it's way slower so
um but it was it took like a painful
week of stuff to do that conversion
because the a lot of the compiler is
about what can we compile right now and
it's all intimately related to that
structure yeah um actually and then
there's other system like while you have
that information there's other systems
that we're using it you know and it was
just really I was supposed to be
enjoying a vacation in Hawaii and I was
painfully actually no that wasn't quite
what this was but you know
um so I want to go back to maybe
something that's more linearized but the
the real observation to make is you know
maybe a lot of
things a lot of things are guaranteed to
actually compile if you have the leaves
right so the main thing that that might
not be ready to compile is an identif
right that just refers to something in
your program uh a stru d reference right
a DOT operator similarly you might not
know the struct yet but beyond that it's
like eh like what are what's the problem
really and so you could imagine
linearizing only those things and then
because identifiers get like look just
look at this right how many times do we
use the word next here um the way we do
it and the way basically everybody does
it that's six different identifiers with
the word next in it and the way I
linearize my thing those are at
arbitrary
positions throughout um this array among
the other nodes because it's just I walk
the tree and get the leaves and put them
in
right if you were just were saying these
are the identifiers we need before we
can proceed because that's the thing
you're most common to block on and then
if you're only worried about those you
could have a much tighter Loop that's
just like looking up names and only
concerned with those data structures
then you might notice that you asked for
the same thing six times because it's
much closer together and you're like oh
yeah there only needs to be one right um
so there's probably a lot of
efficiencies that could happen that way
but it is it's a large structural change
and so I just haven't wanted to do it
yet
um yeah someday I just bra anniversary
edition is coming out on April 30th and
part of the reason it is coming out at
that time is that I'm not rewriting the
core of the the compiler at
all um do you store additional for later
phases in syntax tree what's your
opinion on having multiple internal
representations for different
compilation steps this is something
where so I'm very contrarian by Nature
so when I do something I tend to do the
opposite of the Dragon book right or
whatever and compiler education loves
making a new representation for your
program to do a pass on it right like
Hey we're going to make we've got our
syntax tree now we're going to make a a
control flow graph so that you can
decide where the program goes or
whatever and then we'll make a different
thing out of that and all this and
actually one of the um God I'm blanking
on his name because again I'm old uh
Cliff click who runs a a coffee compiler
Club
stream uh I think it's mostly for his
it's really it's sort of for anyone who
wants to talk about compilers but it
ends up the more motivated people doing
the most work end up being the topic of
conversation and it's so it's usually
his compiler right um but he actually
again there's this weird thing where
really good basic points sometimes get
conflated with other things so he has a
paper called sea of nodes which is about
a different representation that's not
exactly as tree like I guess it's still
right maybe it is a tree I don't I don't
even remember um well it's a c according
to the title but it's not it's not a a
more extremely hierarchical thing but
the actual very good takeaway to take
from that even if you don't want to use
that representation is that when you're
going to compute something like um you
know to do control flow or data flow
analysis you need to know some things
like what code could bring Branch to
this point right where where can we go
after this right and that makes up the
control flow graph and the data flow
graph is like that for you know value
numbers or whatever your representation
is of of what variables could be right
and all of the way the way this is
always taught is you start with a syntax
tree that just exists it's just out in
The Ether it is a primordial syntax tree
and then you Traverse the syntax tree
and you do analysis on it to build these
other graphs and the point is that's
really stupid because for
example um actually I said syntax tree
but often it's later often it's like
semantic you've done like some type
checking and stuff so you know what the
things are right but it's still in a
tree it I I tend to conflate these to go
back to the original question for a
second because we do literally put
everything on the syntax tree node all
the later information of of compilation
goes on there as well there's some ways
in which that's bad um actually to
finish answering that part of the
question
um I guess I just did like the reason I
did that is because I just wanted to be
the polar like I didn't want 17
different trees a that's complicated B
it's really slow you're copying all your
data all these times and I'm like I want
my compiler to be fast so we're just G
to do as little as we have to to do the
work right like that's that should be
for a modern programmer who wants to be
way better than the average programmer
in 2024 theistic you should have is that
you
do what you need in order you need to
have a
clear uh picture of the problem which
sometimes is very difficult and then you
just do as little as you need to to
solve that specific problem that should
be your first step then once you have
that
program you might analyze the
performance and say oh I didn't real I
mean if you realize it's going to be
slow don't do it that way but if you
didn't realize and then you run it on
real world data you have some
information that helps you make it
better that's all great but like there's
there's this Cult of complexity in the
education system for computer science
it's just like [ __ ] yeah dude 17 trees
it's awesome right you're being a
computer scientist when you make all
these trees and it's like I think the
thing is John on that that the cover of
the compiler book there yeah where it
shows where it where it helpfully has
the P the different words on the various
parts of the metaphor so that you're not
confused about what the metaphor is a
lot of people don't know this but
because you can't see it but on the
night's underwear underneath his armor
it does say [ __ ] ton of intermediate
representations that's another tool that
they use in that book to slay the dragon
of compiler complexity of complexity yes
it's by having like 12 different IRS
yeah for every possible thing you might
do but okay so so to get back to the
point that Cliff makes very well which
is an important point which also needs
to be signal
boosted just in the same way we said
parsing precedence is simple a lot of
stuff about compilers is simple and
again it's important because some of
it's really complicated and hard so we
need to identify the simple
things and just understand how simple
they are so all this construction of
control flow graphs and data flow graphs
and the algorithms they give
you are only
necessary
because you didn't have any information
about this tree that you got at the
start because that's how the algorithm
is written in reality and we do this
actually when we do our control flow
representation it's not really a graph
it's like an array of like some values
right
um like for example you have a for Loop
right this comes through in our compiler
it's one node you've got a child that's
like the condition right and then the
then block and the else block and then
maybe some other modifiers are on this
node and we've done all the type
checking so we know the variables are
valid we know what type they are we
actually do some more complex things
where we allow you to overload for Loops
for data structures right and so we know
if that's happening or not then it's
time to Output the code and what does
that look like actually let's take an if
statement if statement is even simpler
it's the simplest one sorry if statement
so you parse it keyword if in C there's
paren whatever you parse those there's a
condition child and then there's a then
block sorry I said then block and else
block for the for loop it's like I've
been playing too many video games um for
Loop sorry we don't do else blocks
python does or whatever we just have a
body of the for Loop for if statement
condition then block else block we know
everything about them and then it's time
to start generating code which is when
what you need control flow and data flow
information for right um you actually
don't really need data flow information
unless you're going to optimize or
control flow information this is all
only about optimization which I don't
even know if they really tell you that
in that book um okay you sort of need
control flow information just to
generate the code at all though right
not really I mean you need jumps and
stuff I mean you
need you need to to know the jump Target
yeah yeah
that's not that's not control flow
because that that exists that exists in
an isolation like
okay yeah
um anyway
uh so my point is just the point that
Cliff makes which is very simple
is um you've got what's called a basic
block in compilers this is another
concept that I wouldn't really argue
with a basic block is just some
statements
where if any of them are going to run
they're all going to run because there's
no branches or whatever actually there's
different kind
of sometimes you could Branch out of a
basic block and you call that a basic
block sometimes you
have a minimal basic block versus a
whatever basic I don't know anyway I for
mine again in in the pursuit of
Simplicity a basic block for me is you
can't Branch into the middle anywhere
but you could leave if you want you
could leave early
right okay
you're generating your bite code or
whatever representation for your if
statement you're going to Output the
condition no matter what because you
can't do anything till you know so you
just that's in your same basic block as
whatever the code was before the if
statement you start outputting the
condition and then you're going to
Branch somewhere right and you're going
to Branch to the then block or the else
block instead of
just making some tree and then later
running analysis on the
tree you know because it's an if
statement okay we're about to make two
new blocks the then block and the else
block okay those are basic
blocks um I think in C isn't this this
block in C the term for like a curly
BRAC and whatever I think so it could be
confusing this is just a basic block
means a very specific thing in compiler
stuff
um a block in C could be composed of
many basic blocks right um
so you have a then block you have an
else block so you do the condition and
then how do you write this if you're
writing your own pseudo machine code
it's like well if the condition is
true well if it's if it's false we jump
over the then block to the else block
right and then at the bottom of the then
block we jump over the else block to
like whatever's afterward right and so
because you're not allowed to jump into
a basic block
when you make a then block that's a new
basic block from the one that had the
condition in it and when you make the
else block that's a new basic block but
you know you know what the parent is and
you
know
um you know they're
uh you know any any childs of these
blocks are going to be determined by
recursive code generation and so like
there is no analysis step to create the
tree is the point like or what ever
whatever your representation is at every
step because you know the functionality
of the node you just do it you just say
oh um you know add these to the
successor list because we created the
blocks when we're processing the if
statement so all these algorithms for
like walking over a tree to do this and
to find like the dominating well I don't
know maybe dominating Frontier still
exists but most of the creation of the
thing is literally just the code that
you would
type to record something in the data
structure of your choice like that is
literally what it is it's insane right
and people just write tons of papers and
books about it it's nutballs um again
it's actually very similar to a thing
one of my game developer articles that I
wrote which was after I got fed up with
all the terrain LOD stuff that I was
doing which was some of my earliest
experience with being disappointed in
computer science papers that promise
performance good performance
um I decided to think about like hey
let's do LOD for terrain is static
meshes right oh but you have to you have
to chop the meshes because the far away
pieces need to be lower res and stuff
and oh that's a hard problem to know how
to stitch those together you got to have
Hur everybody at GDC was telling me that
or not every the few people I talked to
they were like oh yeah you would need a
weird heuristic to whatever and I'm like
wait a minute you had the input mesh
and then you chopped it you like know
what polygons go together and then as
you reduce the L on the other side you
know the source
polygons right that generate you know
like LOD means you turn fine detail into
coar detail so if you have two triangles
and you realize you could make them one
triangle then you you actually know that
information and so if you wanted to
maintain a seam between those two things
of different lods you actually can do it
perfectly with no heris because you made
the lower detail representation so you
just say oh here's the highres
seam the lower these two triangles
collapse into one they had edges on that
seam so make those two edges into like
you know one thing and it was very
simple and that was all it was and it's
like the same thing in compilers it's
kind of
astonishing um sorry that was that was a
long explanation that nobody cares about
and nobody understands because I'm tired
and and rambling so it's what happens
when I play video games and then sleep
for six
hours um let me let's video it wasn't
video games a video game it was a very
specific singular video game a uh stress
testing simulator someone is saying is
it a bad idea to use the correct grammar
for operator precedence okay first of
all uh I'm inclined to ignore this
question I won't but I'm inclined to
ignore the question question because you
saying correct grammar which is like
some kind of Harvard [ __ ] to say right
like yes there are um there is this
Backus now forum for example it's the
most popular way of representing this
kind of grammar for a programming
language what do you what do you mean by
correct
okay um why why are you elevating that
to some it may or may not be a useful
way to represent things for for me I
have never written this out this is you
know what these are is in like a sort of
a pseudo kind of mathy but kind of
programming language form these are like
what the things are in your language
I've literally never written that for
this compiler so I don't I don't care
about this kind of representation so I
object to the word correct it's like
when people say they're making their C++
code const correct I'm like the word
correct there is a propaganda word it is
not describing anything technical
um but okay
so yeah I mean the problem is this is
just going to be really slow like you're
writing a a buttload of if statements
and okay I mean you can do that right
you're gonna you're going to take lots
of Branch prediction failures and even
if you don't it's just a lot of
instructions that you don't need I mean
isn't this also basically like the even
more expanded version of what we read in
that uhing interpreters book like this
is basically that it's that exact code
but you just expanded it
out um well it's also in the opposite
order so we have compare here and then
add here so you go up the file as the
Precedence goes up right but like I said
I mean if you miss that part don't do
this um it's
not it's not the right way to do it I
would say also uh one thing that I find
just
personally as more of a consumer of this
information than a
producer is I find BNF form to be kind
of useless for me to understand what the
heck actually happens in a programming
language like if you present me the BNF
for as much of C++ as you can write it
for which is not all of it yes um it
doesn't really help me no like I can't
really like some things are fairly clear
like it's like oh okay if I just read
like multiply expression I can sort of
understand what the BNF does there but
like go to like type declaration and I'm
like I have no idea how this helps me
like by the time I finish like going
through and going like okay so the con
could could have gone in either order
around wait what's this thing again oh
it's this because you constantly have to
introduce non-terminals yeah to explain
what's going on in the BNF that's sort
of how they work and non-terminals are
by their definition things which often
times don't exist in the actual
programming light like
they don't have an actual like thing a
human would read They're a artificial
category of thing which you then have to
learn what it is so one problem I have
with BNS generally is when people try to
use that as the way to formally Define a
programming language well that may be
fine for ingesting into various tools of
some kind if that's really your thing
yeah that's fine but as something that
humans work with I don't find them to be
very good yeah if I'm going to learn a
new programming language I don't want to
see that at all right I don't want to
see it at all yeah the one thing that
you could say it's useful for is like
after I've designed my language and it's
kind of done I want to analyze my
grammar to make sure I didn't like do
something stupid you know like maybe
there's a
weird see this is a very Hy this is what
people say I guess like last time I
argued with somebody who's very
argumentative that you know um who I
haven't spoken to in years at this point
um okay making this argument I know who
it is yes and um but it's just a very
hypothetical case because like look if
if there's a weird so so one thing you
know the whole thing we were saying
before about oh there's a shift reduce
conflict or whatever
right the the BNF of the language and
then going through this kind of process
of you know breaking it down into token
by token and then analyzing like what
what is the scope of all things that
could happen next right is an analysis
you can do with that representation and
then you could print or you know
essentially a shift reduce conflict
report or whatever of
like these are the weird things in your
grammar but the thing is in reality
that's never going to be a problem
because if you used your programming
language at all you would notice that
you tried to type something and it
didn't come out the way you wanted and
then you would change
it and so it's like it's a it's an
academic solution to a nonpr in a sense
like if if the destruction of the
Earth was at stake and I was like I need
to make really sure that I didn't make a
weird mistake here I would totally go do
that
right but like that's just not how
things are I also don't know how useful
even it is in the case where where the
Earth is about to be destroyed which of
course happens often um and that is that
it doesn't really tell you much about
the part that you're likely to actually
have problems with which is the rest of
the compiler so it's like having this
like extremely formal description that
leaves out basically any semantic
checking at all and then the the
explanation for well how do we do the
semantic check like what's the notation
for the semantic checking part they're
like well we don't have that is not like
that doesn't help like that's just like
you you made this artificial thing that
we have to then go learn as a separate
exercise that actually doesn't capture
most of the problem so what was the
point like yeah if you got to the point
where you could describe the entire
correctness of a programming language in
some kind of really concise notation
then that's maybe more interesting um
and you know maybe some theoretical CS
people have actually done that but
that's not BNF so BNF is just kind of
frustrating to me most the time I don't
see yeah like I said I don't see much of
the point in BNF except to prove that
you went to computer school um I have
much more Sympathy for the people who
are trying to do like program prover
systems yeah and that's more interesting
I also think that those are a little
impractical at the current time unless
we make some big breakthrough but at
least that makes sense to me I'm like
okay I get it yes it is very hard for me
to know if my program is correct in fact
actually no it's easy for me to know
that it's it's not correct it's got
problems I just don't know what the
problems are okay right
yeah so so I'm very sympathetic to that
initiative
which the BNF is like maybe more of a
cargo cult version of that but you know
like here's the
thing all that stuff goes way back into
the 70s and the 60s and maybe even the
50s when
like it was like maybe computer language
is a little bit like human language
right and you had all these cognitive
scientists like trying to do grammar for
English and stuff like whatever like all
that stuff is kind of mixed
together um and again I don't put the
fault
on um any of the people who came up with
these ideas right I do put the fault on
our system both academic and Industrial
to the extent it participates in this of
propagating these weird incorrect
Notions of what you should be doing
right that's the part that failed having
different ideas about how to represent
your grammar is great like there might
be some cool ones that nobody's thought
of and it would be good to add those to
the world if if they have something to
add but after that there needs to be
some diligent step of the collective
intelligence wherein we decide correctly
and
accurately what is really the good way
to do things and we've been pretty bad
at that as far as I can tell yeah it's
it's it's piss poor yeah uh here's a
concrete question how do you parse so
someone is asking about dot we talked
about dot struct references before
there's a couple of constructs we have
we have like A.B that's a struct
reference just so I can see and then our
struct literals because we allow you to
use them as an expression and like infer
the type and stuff and I didn't want to
worry about weird parsing ambiguities
for now we put a dot in front of our
brace so if you have a struct type and
um you know you could have your your
elements in here
um you know and they could be different
types or whatever um and they're just
asking what does that do so if this is a
struct right then this is a value copy
of that struct with the fields filled in
by these values and you could use names
if you want here you could say like name
equals hello and these could be out of
order if you specify to you whatever s s
is a type name or an identifier
uh those are the same thing okay so it's
it's an identifier that has to be
evaluatable as a a constant and it has
to refer to a type right okay so it
could be it could be something that's
just referring to a type or it could be
an actual type name but it just has to
be something that becomes that can be
you can get a list of fields from it yes
the compiler knows what stru this is at
compile time is the point right got it
it could be a more complex like we have
compile time executions you could run
some stuff right right whatever um so
they're just asking how do you know the
difference and the answer is just when
you see a DOT so so we have dot in our
binary operator parsing but when we see
a DOT we just look one token ahead and
we say is there a brace it's very simple
right if there's a brace it's this
otherwise par an expression because this
like open brace whatever closed brace is
not really an expression in the way that
we have this programmed as Casey was
saying before you could play games about
what's an expression and what's not and
yeah you know I just chose not to do
that for this so this is this is a very
just like the for Loop example we were
talking about where you have specialized
parsing that's exactly what this is it's
like we go into a special mode that does
this thing and then we return that back
out um and that's sort of the here's the
thing here's the interesting thing is in
designing your grammar so I you know I
put the dot here just to make it easy I
don't know you could you could maybe say
that but then as you're developing a
language you have to deal with like
you're kind of asking for it at some
point like oh now this kind of
expression looks like that kind of
expression and it's not clear which is
which and you have maybe if it is clear
to the programmer you have to do more
work to like make the code look more
ahead to determine which one it is or
whatever but the thing is you don't
really want to be playing that game
anyway like you want people to be able
to just look at the program prr and know
what it means right and the more there's
a parallelism where the more that you
have to make the parser do crazy stuff
to look ahead to determine maybe this is
something weird someone looking at the
code may not understand that either
right um and so you just want things to
be simple to read and simple to
understand and that tends to correspond
to simple grammars that's actually why
for example so C has this is a putting
this dot here is a kind of a defensive
grammar design where it's like I just
like it better if it's clear C has that
in like you know if statements and uh
you know they have parentheses around
them why well because sometimes what's
inside the parentheses might look like
like if there's a un operator afterward
because you don't have to put braces
afterward if there's a un operator and
you have an expression inside the
parentheses it might and the parentheses
weren't there it might look like a
binary operator and we're we're just
going to say screw it there's
parentheses es and that's how we solve
this problem and sometimes you do that
um sometimes people get on my case that
they wish there was a little less
punctuation but I'm like we could look
at that later in the meantime I just
want it to be very clear what everything
is and I don't want these weird problems
and I don't want people to be writing
code we exactly had one exact we don't
have that many un operators that are
that you tend to use in that case we
don't have the parentheses which is why
I'm saying all this um
there was one Unity operator that was
causing problems and we just changed it
to to a post uh postorder unit operator
and then that problem goes away
um
okay do you do something in crazy in the
lexer to maximize throughput No like
lexer is just really fast
um I
don't like the par is really fast and
it's way slower than the lexer um one
thing we do like we don't allocate a
trillion tokens right we reuse there's
like you know some number of tokens that
we allowed to look ahead and there's
just like a ring buffer of them right
and so um we're not allocating we're
especially not calling Malik per token
but we're not actually allocating new
tokens um we are allocating subdata of
tokens so if you have an identifier we
need to know the name of the identifier
we just make that little string some
where that's cheap to allocate and
pointed it
um yeah uh shout out to Coffee compiler
club by the way they they could use more
viewership it is a niche topic but they
they're on YouTube let's let's find a
YouTube video
since they tend to be pretty long and in
depth updated seven days ago yeah
they're still doing it I wasn't sure but
yeah they just talk about compiler
stuffff every week it is invite only to
be on the
thing um so probably no bozos but if you
want to watch them it's pretty easy it's
just as you can see it's a niche topic
like 300 views 400
views yeah some of them I guess get more
uh yeah we'll post this on YouTube are
you bored Casey do you want to cut it
here or do you want to keep going what's
what's your level of Interest I mean I'm
happy to do whatever you're up for it s
it sounds like if there's more
interesting questions that's fine with
me I don't have much to add right I'm
only here to ask questions you're not
you're not in the middle of yeah doing
these things um I I will say that
starting I think I didn't have enough
breakfast and I have a lack of sugar to
the brain which is why I started
munching truffles truffles yeah so I
feel like a couple of the answers that
I've been giving in the past q&as for 15
20 minutes were a little too Meandering
and a little too like not quite the best
answer but well maybe that's the end
then maybe let's see if there's good
questions okay yeah that's the thing is
I don't want to put bad answers to
questions out
there so I saw as I'm scrolling through
the chat Oxford comma correct was
something that somebody
said yeah what if you develop things
that work with various languages so you
need not one parser but a dozen do you
think writing them individually is
better anyway as opposed to using parser
generator yes but also if you find
yourself using a dozen programming
languages you're doing something super
super super
wrong editor an editor might be an
example though like right like I'm
making I'm making Sublime I'm the author
of sublime and everyone's like I want
syntax highlighting for squeam Lang and
you're like I don't even know what
squeam Lang is but now I'm pulling up
the you know web page for that yeah what
you know what do you do in those cases
and like probably a parser generator
would be great but the problem is
usually that they don't work very well
like the problem is not that it wouldn't
be great if there was some magic way to
make parsers quickly the problem is
there isn't well there there isn't so
this is one thing that I wanted to say
before too because like you know our
parser right now is 6,000
lines I'm pretty sure if we use a parser
generator it would be longer
substantially right because you have to
do all this interfacing with the thing
um and then you have to do all this
making your own structure to cope that
the structure of the thing isn't what
you wanted and it just yeah I've done it
enough times to know but here's the
other
thing
um like we talked before about how error
messages are important
right doing syntax highlighting
correctly
is while somebody's in the middle of
typing stuff that is not complete right
is sort of equivalent to generating a
good error message like there's a way in
which those problems are very similar
where I don't want my highlighting to
get all freaking stupid just
because you know I don't know you you
like got a parthy somewhere or whatever
yes but that's the thing is if you use a
parser generator that is what you will
get out of it right and then you could
add some code when you see a conflict to
like try TR to do something but you
don't have because this is the thing
when you write the code yourself in
recursive descent form which I will say
once again is too complicated of a name
you're just calling functions that parse
the things they should call it calling
functions that parse the things
parser okay that is what it
is when you do that you know exactly
what you're doing you have all the
context right um it's just much easier
to to give high quality responses and I
mean I I have not made an editor that
does syntax highlighting but if I were
to I would absolutely um do the grammars
I mean if you like there's this whole
question okay what if what if you're
releasing the editor for everybody and
you want to provide a way for people to
contribute and stuff and even then is
the contribution
like just them being able to make some
code that simply parses the thing or do
they have to learn some weird ass you
know parser generator thing and what you
know I would also point out that like
it's it's worse I think even than you're
making it out to be John and you're
already making it out to be bad uh which
is that like in a lot of circumstances
that I can think of where you're trying
to ship something that uses multiple
parsers they are like you pointed out
working on something that's under
construction they're like you know some
kind of like checking tools or syntax
highlighting or things like this and uh
if you take the example of like syntax
highlighting you know there is no way to
parse a file for syntax highlighting
often times there's things like pound if
blocks in it oh yeah right yeah yeah and
and or like you know stuff like that and
it's like well technically there is a
particular way that you parse that which
is you find out what the pound defines
are and you actually evaluate the if
blocks and that's the parts of the file
that's what the compiler will use but
that's not the best thing to show The
View like the user would like to see as
close as possible as you can figure out
what a human would want highlighted for
every part of the if blocks even the
parts that aren't actually in involved
in that particular compiler in that
particular pass and so you know it's
like it's a different problem and
particularly ill suited to something
like a parer generator because you're
trying to do sort of of like intuitive
stuff it's more like chat GP than it is
like uh like Yak right and so you know
her istics are going to be involved no
matter what and you want to make it as
easy to do heris as you can actually
this is reminding me of the of all
things the uh gameplay code engine for
the sooon game actually okay because
it's like if you can do the strict core
rule set and it works and you're not
seeing any problems then absolutely do
that
and because you want to be correct right
you don't want to be engaging heris on
something that parses correctly right
but as soon as you hit something that
doesn't parse correctly it's like okay
you want theistic to kind of plug in and
take over and be like oh you know this
looks like we were maybe going to do
this construct but it didn't some piece
of punctuation is missing or something
right
yep and um obviously that the thing
about those her istics is they never end
like you can make a better and better
user experience by layering more and
more of them maybe at some point you go
way too far like Microsoft with trying
to type into visual studio and nobody
wants to use it anymore but um if you're
if you're act that's just making good
versus bad decisions right but that's
actually what the sooon game engine
works like is like look here's there's a
strict stuff that has to happen to
maintain the Integrity of the moves
but for better game feel we can plug in
little rule exceptions
that are allowed to like let things
happen and then clean up the the result
it's a little bit of a different thing
but it it reminds me of the same thing
and
but it's a little bit different because
in the soan case we have to be correct
in the end no matter what like there is
a correct answer whereas in the text
editing it's like yeah I don't know I
it's
yeah uh did this rewrite speed up
slightly the compiler um I haven't
noticed but probably not like again the
parser is pretty fast
um it's all the later parts of
compilation that are slow I did say 10%
was getting memory but we still need to
get the same amount of memory like we
haven't changed the tree representation
or whatever here right so the you know
the actual um the actual code that runs
in the compiler is very fast compared to
the stuff that type checks like type
checking is our entire bottleneck um
type checking is the hardest most R see
I can't even speak anymore it's no blood
to the brain most rats nesty part of the
compiler um so yeah anything any changes
the only way that I anticipate a speed
difference is if somebody puts really
dumb stuff into the parser and slows it
way down but you're not really going to
see speed UPS from that um do you
tokenize the whole thing all at once or
as the parser asked for tokens um I do
it as you ask for tokens which may or
may not be good um again it might be
faster so the thing is because your
tokens have a clear this is not true in
C you could probably make it true a
little bit in C we talked about this
last time about
how parsing doesn't have to be the final
word in what things are you could like
reinterpret them later by changing the
tree around um so in C the classic thing
is it does matter that something's a
name of a type that's not the same thing
as a variable name and there's stuff
that you wouldn't be able to parse if
you didn't know what all the names of
the types are and see
um so there you you can't strictly
generate tokens ahead of time without
parsing
if you have a token for name of a type
and a different token right for a
different thing but you could have a
token that just says this looks like an
identifier maybe it's a variable maybe
it's a type name I don't know and then
there's some if statements that run when
you see that right and and that's when
but but that could be generated by the
lexer ahead of time because it doesn't
need to know the types right the point
being you could have if you were in a
very parallelism mindset you could just
have one thread just blast through the
source file generate all the tokens for
the source file and those are just
sitting there linearly in memory right
you could use just you know virtual alic
or whatever to just put the tokens next
to each other and they're just like all
there that would be much bigger than the
source file um but source files don't
tend to be that big um and then you
could have the parser just read linearly
those tokens um I don't do that
because like I don't again it's not a
speed problem and it just someday if
that ever comes up as anywhere in the
top 500 issues with the compiler I could
think about it right that also doesn't
sound faster right it sounds slower what
you just described I mean it's sort of
like you are jumping around between
different code and maybe the has its own
data structures and maybe the parser
does so that you're touching different
pieces of memory but modern CPUs and
modern caches like it's not like parsing
is that complicated it's not like Lexing
is that complicated modern CPUs are
going to be able to hold all that easily
I would say I not having done the
performance analysis my guess is that
it's all fine and it doesn't matter um
and that's why I didn't really think
seriously about it's just fun to think
about though like oh yeah I could just I
could just really have a tight thing
that just cranks and in fact in fact I
could split the source file up at new
line boundaries into multiple and have
multiple threads generate this long
series of tokens in parallel and just
really up the token rate and you would
literally never notice this in the
resulting speed of the compiler because
well a is Casey said it may not actually
be faster I don't think it'll be faster
but B it's negligible in terms of the
time spent by the compiler
anyway don't make things more
complicated than they have to be
um someone's asking again is it faster
it doesn't
matter someone says I like grammar
specifications since you can then use a
parsel generator and you are good to go
cool story bro
um I think you have a definition of good
to go that is very different from my
definition of good to go maybe as long
as good to go means means you're good to
go rewrite it as something better you're
good to go get a job at
McDonald's oh God
okay
okay not that there's anything wrong
with having a job at McDonald's you're
good to go work somewhere else is I
guess what you're saying yes yeah um
you've shown your token structure in the
original parser's video what is the atom
star is that a string that's basically
um it was a way of interning the strings
on the lexer side so that you don't have
as many strings that you're allocating
and stuff um I don't have a separate
structure for that anymore um sometimes
I make decisions for clarity and then
later I'm like oh that actually wasn't
confusing right so you know we have a
car star for like what is the name of
this thing and that gets intered locally
to the lexer um now there can be
multiple threads parsing stuff because
we just load up a bunch of files and
parse them simultaneously and so in turn
for that Lex so the parser and the lexer
are like bundled although they're
essentially the same thing as far as
anyone should be concerned and so
um there's essentially a local cache of
what all the strings are for there but
you don't want to like synchronize that
with other threads because that just
seems like a lose uh so
so they're like kind of
intered
um
but and is that a good idea maybe not
anymore um like it used to be that
things were globally interned and what
that meant
was um you know like when you're
comparing
identifiers uh if you want to know that
this is the Declaration of this
identifier you just check if the string
pointer is the same right and that's
what that Adam struct was that like sort
of wrapped that to make it clear that
that's what was going on um but once I
went to a more parallel design for the
parsers it's like is that really worth
rescuing probably not because you don't
like do that many string
Compares and large name spaces are in a
hash table anyway and you have a hash
table for the identifier and you can
compare that to see if it's the same
so there's not really much like the
complexity you would lose in making
threads synchronize with each other
other to make sure they had the right
canonical version of an identifier is
like that's just way worse than whatever
the gain would be I think but again we
have never we have literally never been
hardcore about making this compiler go
fast it's like there have been a few
times a couple years apart each who I
spent a couple days doing some stuff to
make it faster and you
know you can compare the speed that you
see to something like GCC or clang and
decide
what you think of it um but but it's
just to say that we could have much
greater levels of speed if we actually
did that like we haven't designed for
Speed I don't even know it's been
complicated enough to to solve the
fundamental problem of just implementing
the semantics of this language that I
just I mean I know I'm designing for not
pathologically dumb and slow but we're
not designed for fast yet that I
hopefully will come later
um
someday someday not too long in the
future I'm going to believe I'm going to
believe uh could you give us your
thoughts about IR if it's a valid thing
and generate bite code yeah we generate
bite code um I think that's the main so
you have to kind of understand what is
the job of that right and it it'll make
sense if you understand what it's for so
if you want a compiler that lets you
compile your code for multiple CPUs or
even you know well let's just say
multiple CPUs keep it simple and the
CPUs are very different from each other
and they have different instructions
that don't necessarily have analoges of
each other sometimes
um and you also don't want to have to
completely rewrite your whole compiler
next time there's a new CPU there's not
been a lot of CPU Innovation lately it's
all incremental but maybe someday once
AIS are all designing CPUs instead of
people will actually make some progress
again right um except the AIS are all
example
based they'll just be re done versions
of the existing CPUs they'll make amd64
instruction set except there's three
more padding bites on the front that
like tell you different things yeah um
so uh so what the bite code is for is to
let you do instruction-based code
generation which is is very important
like you know your computer actually
runs
instructions that you could sort of
write them out one per line and they're
relatively simple compared to a higher
level program and like that's just the
way the CPU operates and so the job of
the compiler is in some sense to bridge
the gap between text that some dude
wrote right and then that list of
instructions that the CPU understands
and the step the steps that we've been
talking about so far are mostly about so
first of all Parson getting that tree
representation what is the tree the tree
is a representation of what has to
happen when but it's not not that linear
you have to like do a walk on it and you
probably have to do you know once you
look up the identifiers and figure out
what the function overloading are and
whatever happens you end up with a
result later that's like more like the
semantic version of the tree right the
semantic version of the tree has all
these blocks and stuff but not not the
basic blocks we were talking about but
like blocks of instructions um and then
you have to go somehow from here's an
array of instructions that are still
represented as tree nodes to
like something more like instructions
from a CPU and and then you could do
that separately per CPU you could say
okay here's my back end that walks the
tree and generates code for x86 here's
one that does it for arms and the
problem with that is that you will end
up with way way way way way too much of
the
compiler uh duplicated between all
those and it'll just be a huge mess
because it's just an interesting
situation where there are quite a few
optimizations that you want to do with a
particular CPU in mind but there are
really most optimizations that you want
to do are not even particular to a CPU
it's just like
hey I realized that inside this
scope I Define this variable once and
then nobody else can write to it and
that means a lot of things in terms of
you know what instructions we would
generate and that's invariant to
whatever the CPU is that's running the
code and so that kind of optimization
you want to happen you want to write
that once hopefully in as simple a way
as
possible because there's going to be
actually a large number of these right
and all the things we alluded to before
like a data flow graph or control flow
graph or whatever are used to figure out
these
things like what can we rely on that's
true so that we know so that we can be
smarter about generating code because
what makes code dumb and Bloated is like
if you can't be sure about something
right so the C keyword restrict is like
a
Band-Aid I I don't mean that too
pejorative because it's like I'm not
sure what else you would do in that
situation but it's a way of saying like
look you can assume certain things about
this pointer so um you know if you're
reading some other value you don't have
to assume for example that a right
through this pointer change this other
seemingly unrelated value if it seems to
be unrelated it really is unrelated so
you don't have to keep reloading it all
the time and whatever to make sure um
all that kind of stuff the CPU doesn't
matter right and so you want to
implement it and debug it and make it
work well right and then so that
shouldn't stop you from doing CPU
specific optimizations but those happen
in like the actual back end right but
the bite code instructions um get you a
substantial amount of the distance from
well you know from the semantic tree to
the actual instructions on the CPU right
and then it's much easier to say oh I
have I have like a Vite code for some
fictitious virtual machine machine of my
own that's a an array of
instructions with my own you know the
way it's implemented is there's a
program counter or whatever and it's
just
running you know in in a in an
interpreter
essentially mapping from that to
instructions on a CPU is a much much
closer mapping and and so then you can
get away with
uh having a lot less code than you would
otherwise
right um how do you organize identifiers
in the scope hierarchy it's really
stupid I I don't it's it's not good
we'll put it that
way um how to make a good optimizing
compiler I mean that's the hard part so
you know earlier we I kept saying
parsing is the easy part other things
are hard really the only hard thing in
compilers is optimization well and
proving your program is correct which is
basically impossible right now
um those are the things that are hard
like all the other stuff is easy um I
mean maybe maybe like design is an art
so you could say designing the right
thing is hard but in terms of actually
what you type
um actually it's sort of a lie the the
other thing that's hard is just if your
feature set is really ambitious as ours
is um you just end up with this kind of
car crash in the middle of the inter
section where all sorts of stuff is
happening all the time and like all like
part of the beauty of a programming
language is like all these things are
just Expressions right
and they interact with each other and
and you have these features that you can
use on the expressions in your language
or whatever and the more features that
you give people the more that they have
to work all the time in concert with
each other and that generates a kind of
an N squared explosion of potential
problems
that's actually the other hard thing
besides optimization is just but that's
the same thing as in other program
that's the same thing as in video games
right is it's just like at some point
what we're trying to do is really
complicated and it's becomes difficult
to understand even what we're doing and
how to do it well and that's always
especially these days why I'm very
concerned with simplifying things all
the time because I've just suffered
through too much of like oh all these
things are way more complicated at than
they need to be it's causing
problems but bad problems and then
really bad problems right so bad
problems are like oh it's taking 30% 50%
longer because of all this friction 90%
longer those are bad you might run out
of money or get depressed and never
finish your project but the worst
problem
is like I have in my brain some Maximum
ability to
visualize something that I could work on
right
and like if I could somehow go to the
gym and work that out and and make it
better which I think is what programming
does like I'm not claiming this is fixed
but it probably slowly grows over time
although someday maybe I'm getting old
and it'll shrink but I feel like it's
still growing um so what I can even
ignoring the friction component what I
could even ever accomplish is kind of
bound by my ability to harness a complex
situation and deal with it mentally
right um and so there's there's only a
certain amount of space in there and if
you take up a bunch of that space with
stupid stuff being a lot more
complicated than it needs to be there's
less space for other stuff and so
the the total functionality that you're
able to do is smaller right because you
just wasted a bunch of
it um and I don't think people take that
very seriously and I think because well
it's it's in a different guys right
because I've done a lot of stuff where
I'm the main programmer I see that very
directly right um when you have a
company like you know Google or someone
Twitter old Twitter
especially
bang it doesn't fail in the same way um
what happens is you actually hire more
and more people and then those people
know less
and the the quality of the product
starts just sliding downhill because
there's
no there's
like making complex software work well
is a coordination problem like there's
all these issues that need to be handled
and there need to be things that handle
them and those wires need to be like all
hooked up
and that can get very complicated and at
some point if there's a lot of people
with small enough responsibility those
people can't see this well enough and so
they just do their local area of it and
it screws up other
things and just
nobody nobody even like sees the
perspective that would have avoided that
and
so I don't know I I think that's the
number one problem in software actually
and llm someone's going to say llms llms
don't actually understand anything
currently so they can't help you with
that maybe someday we will solve Ai and
will help you but right now it
doesn't all right I feel like we've been
going a long time it's been two hour no
three hours three hours I think yeah
dude I'm we're cutting into my video
game playing
time uh here's the thing though John is
I have seen you uh your stream being
titled or saying that you are going to
escape from tarov and you clearly have
not escaped because if you're still
there if you're you're still playing I
mean what's the explanation well you see
you must be really lousy at this video
game if you can't escape after this many
hours you just have to the only thing
the game is called is escape from
darkov yeah well it's like it's like
slaying the complexity of compiler
design with ler parser generator and
syntax directed translation if it didn't
work the first time you just got to keep
swinging that ler parser generator sword
one of those times y it'll work
yep all right thank you everybody I do
have to say
um some of my answers were not that good
es especially in the latter half so um I
I regret this but um at the same time
this is just what we're able to do in
like this is not my job and I have all
this stuff I have to do and I do want to
someday write a compiler book because I
think I think it would be different from
everybody else's and I think it would be
a good contribution and that that will
be much more
premeditated um and the cover will be
awesome what we like the cover will be
amazing I don't know what it'll be but
it'll be amazing that's right yeah all
right but thanks for coming by and
so what I would like to end with an
exhortation oh of
please for this entire class of things
so again to review for people who
weren't
here the entire point of this was how
actually simple this parsing precedence
thing is that everybody's not everybody
but most people have made a big deal out
of and and how difficult it is to find
the right information and
culturally we need to recognize that
this is a problem like a lot of things
are actually pretty
simple and for some reason we're not
doing a good job of understanding those
things collectively as like everybody
and so one thing to do is when you find
something like this that's actually
simple now you don't want to be you
don't want to be a bozo and claim
something is really simple when it's not
because some things are complicated but
when things are really
simple just helping to signal boost the
fact that they're simple and they don't
require you to get a degree in you know
parsing science or whatever to know that
times goes before plus like that's just
it's just not how it is but you would
think it was and a lot of people who got
computer science degrees think it that's
how it is um but the point is there's
many things like this and if you could
pitch in and let people know when things
are
simple that's great and it's fun to do
that's the thing I mean Casey could
probably vouch for this because you do a
lot more of this now these days than me
of just like explaining stuff to people
it's like finding a good
explanation that's as simple as you
could make it and making sure you really
understand it and then presenting it
even though I mean again I went through
an emac file with like some trees as
like slashes so it's not like I wrote a
book again but like it's an enjoyable
process and you understand it better at
the end but then you feel good because
it's like look I gave people this thing
right and so we need more of that and
less of like I'm writing this thing to
show everybody I'm
smart that's what I would say all
yeah also I guess one problem that we
have as well uh so so I mean not to can
keep this discussion going any longer
since it's been too long already but
um I think it's harder than your exert
makes it out to be though because like I
mean we literally just had a thing on
Twitter where someone was like I figured
out how to check if a points in a
polygon and it was like the worst
algorithm I've literally ever seen that
but that guy was not really a programmer
whatever and it's just the problem is
that that knowing when something is
simple and easy to understand is itself
a very hard thing to do and most people
can't do it they think they have found a
good explanation and it's awful like I
don't think the people who wrote The
Dragon book think that their
explanations are awful but they are
right and so I don't know like the
problem is harder you're no I agree with
that out and I don't know what the
solution I don't know what if there is a
solution I think there is incremental
Improvement that can be made that causes
feedback that accelerates the
Improvement so the problem is really
that the culture is broken right and
it's broken for a lot of reasons this is
just merely one of the loes of
Brokenness of of what's happening right
um but it's a it's a major one really um
and like if we kind of had a no [ __ ]
culture in programming which there used
to be like I caught the tail end of that
in college right it was still kind of
gone by the time I was there but um you
know nowadays it's the opposite it's
like programming is like full [ __ ]
fire hose culture right it's like
somehow
inverted and you know I it doesn't have
to require being blunt or mean but just
like having a low
tolerance for nonsense or having a low
tolerance well here's the thing how does
something like the Dragon book propagate
it's like
well a lot of things have to go wrong
it's like first of all the better
explanations have to be ignored right
somehow and
then people have to think that this is
actually a good enough explanation that
doesn't requ improvement over the
decades that it's been used right um and
how do they think that do they read the
explanation and think they understand it
right I
mean I would claim like there are
different levels of understanding but I
would claim ultimately that the answer
has to be no
because if
you if you look at all this complexity
that you're building in order to do this
simple thing it's like but wait I know
what I can Pro that was the realization
I had in college after doing like five
languages or something was like wait I
know what I could program and I know
what this thing is producing and it's
worse than what I could program that's
some kind of synthesis that happens
right that synthesis is broken for
everything almost
um
so we need to get that back I don't know
like maybe this is too rambling but
there's just issues like maybe
maybe and again we've talked about this
before but maybe the fundamental
fundamental issue
is
um that the culture of programming needs
to be built
around acknowledgment of clearly
demonstrated
quality right because like if you had if
you had an MMA cage match between ler
parser generator and like hand coded
thing like the hand coded thing would
win on every metric actually right like
literally it would win on speed it would
win on um time to successfully create
the thing it would win on uh it ability
it would lose on one thing ability to
publish papers uh no it would lose on um
incremental so it's very hard actually
to write uh an incremental top down
parser that can stop at any point it's
harder yeah just already does it's like
it or it is that by Design like you just
get that for free yeah so that's the one
thing I could think of that's like top
down it's much harder to write a top
down re uh stop anywhere parser that can
just like take a new token arbitrarily
as like an input generally without
having to because because it uses the
program stack I mean that's just kind of
how that is yeah I see the point um I
will just say that because I haven't
thought about the
problem um I'm not sure that it's
actually all that hard simply because
like that's easier than the freaking uh
typee checking stuff that we do which
has to stop anywhere so you know um I'm
just saying it's not it's easier in LR
because it already works that way well
let's put it this way it has a state
table so it's done doesn't have to do
anything you you would have to add like
the code that we showed today would not
do that would not work yeah you have to
add stuff to it is my only point but
anyway keep going um but it may not even
be that much but the point being like
that's that's just not the culture
somehow and the culture is just you make
claims and then people believe the
claims and the claims act as propaganda
and that's how everything gets popular
and I it's just really harmful and I
don't know at this point it's nothing I
haven't said before
but the end
all right all right thanks Casey for
coming by and talking about this for
several hours oh no problem thanks for I
think they were good no but I I like the
like as someone who does not work on
parsers I appreciate new explanations of
them because you know if I ever actually
do decide to go write a parser this I I
am almost certainly in a much better
position well I could recommend you a
book right
here it's got excellent computer
Graphics yes
yes yeah all right thanks everybody for
coming by we'll post this on YouTube
later because you surely missed a lot of
it because it's three hours yep thanks
take it easy everyone yeah